<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Miscellaneous</db:title>
<db:productname>QDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.14.2 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>QDoc Manual</db:titleabbrev>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="11-qdoc-commands-specialcontent.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="prev" xlink:title="Special Content"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="21-0-qdoc-creating-dita-maps.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="next" xlink:title="Creating DITA Maps"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>QDoc Manual.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">&lt;Unknown command&gt;<db:code>contentspage</db:code></db:emphasis>QDoc Manual</db:para>
<db:para>These commands provide miscellaneous functions connected to the visual appearance of the documentation, and to the process of generating the documentation.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="annotatedlist-command"/>
<db:section xml:id="annotatedlist">
<db:title>\annotatedlist</db:title>
<db:para>The \annotatedlist command expands to a list of the members of a group, each member listed with its <db:emphasis>brief</db:emphasis> text. Below is an example from the Qt Reference Documentation:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    ...
    \section1 Drag and Drop Classes

    These classes deal with drag and drop and the necessary mime type
    encoding and decoding.

    \annotatedlist draganddrop

* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>This generates a list of all the C++ classes and/or QML types in the <db:emphasis>draganddrop</db:emphasis> group. A C++ class or QML type in the <db:emphasis>draganddrop</db:emphasis> group will have <db:emphasis>\ingroup draganddrop</db:emphasis> in its <db:emphasis>\class</db:emphasis> or <db:emphasis>\qmltype</db:emphasis> comment.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="generatelist-command"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="generatelist">
<db:title>\generatelist</db:title>
<db:para>The \generatelist command expands to a list of links to the documentation entities in a group. Below is an example from the Qt Reference Documentation:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \page classes.html
    \title All Classes

    For a shorter list that only includes the most
    frequently used classes, see \l{Qt's Main Classes}.

    \generatelist classes Q
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>This generates the <db:emphasis>All Classes</db:emphasis> page. The command accepts the following arguments:</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="table-example"/>
<db:section xml:id="annotatedclasses">
<db:title>annotatedclasses</db:title>
<db:para>The annotatedclasses argument provides a table containing the names of all the classes, and a description of each class. Each class name is a link to the class's reference documentation. For example:</db:para>
<db:informaltable style="generic">
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>QDial</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>Rounded range control (like a speedometer or potentiometer)</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>QDialog</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>The base class of dialog windows</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>QDir</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>Access to directory structures and their contents</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
</db:informaltable>
<db:para>A C++ class is documented with the <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#class-command">\class</db:link> command. The annotation for the class is taken from the argument of the class comment's <db:link xlink:href="11-qdoc-commands-specialcontent.xml#brief-command">\brief</db:link> command.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="annotatedexamples">
<db:title>annotatedexamples</db:title>
<db:para>The annotatedexamples argument provides a complete list of all examples as a set of tables containing the titles of all the examples, and a description of each example. Each title is a link to the example's documentation.</db:para>
<db:para>A separate table for each module (that has documented examples) is generated, provided that the module has defined a navigation.landingpage configuration variable. The <db:emphasis>landingpage</db:emphasis> variable is used as a title for a header that precedes each table.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="annotatedattributions">
<db:title>annotatedattributions</db:title>
<db:para>The annotatedattributions argument provides a complete list of all attributions as a set of tables containing the titles of all the attributions, and a description of each attribution. Each title is a link to the attribution's page.</db:para>
<db:para>A separate table for each module (that has attributions) is generated, provided that the module has defined a navigation.landingpage configuration variable. The <db:emphasis>landingpage</db:emphasis> variable is used as a title for a header that precedes each table.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="list-example"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="classes-op-lt-op-prefix-op-gt-op">
<db:title>classes &lt;prefix&gt;</db:title>
<db:para>The classes argument provides a complete alphabetical list of the classes. The second argument, &lt;prefix&gt;, is the common prefix for the class names. The class names will be sorted on the character that follows the common prefix. e.g. The common prefix for the Qt classes is Q. The common prefix argument is optional. If no common prefix is provided, the class names will be sorted on their first character.</db:para>
<db:para>Each class name becomes a link to the class's reference documentation. This command is used to generate the <db:emphasis>All Classes</db:emphasis> page this way:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \page classes.html
    \title All Classes
    \ingroup classlists

    \brief Alphabetical list of classes.

    This is a list of all Qt classes. For classes that
    have been deprecated, see the \l{Obsolete Classes}
    list.

    \generatelist classes Q
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>A C++ class is documented with the <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#class-command">\class</db:link> command.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="classesbymodule">
<db:title>classesbymodule</db:title>
<db:para>When this argument is used, a second argument is required, which specifies the module whose classes are to be listed. QDoc generates a table containing those classes. Each class is listed with the text of its <db:link xlink:href="11-qdoc-commands-specialcontent.xml#brief-command">\brief</db:link> command.</db:para>
<db:para>For example, this command can be used on a module page as follows:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \page phonon-module.html
    \module Phonon
    \title Phonon Module
    \ingroup modules

    \brief Contains namespaces and classes for multimedia functionality.

    \generatelist{classesbymodule Phonon}

...

* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Each class that is a member of the specified module must be marked with the <db:link xlink:href="19-qdoc-commands-grouping.xml#inmodule-command">\inmodule</db:link> command in its \class comment.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="qmltypesbymodule">
<db:title>qmltypesbymodule</db:title>
<db:para>Similar to classesbymodule argument, but used for listing the QML types from the QML module specified with the second argument.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Support for this argument was introduced in QDoc 5.6.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="jstypesbymodule">
<db:title>jstypesbymodule</db:title>
<db:para>Similar to classesbymodule argument, but used for listing the JavaScript types from the module specified with the second argument.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Support for this argument was introduced in QDoc 5.6.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="examplefiles-op-op-regular-expression-op-op">
<db:title>examplefiles [regular_expression]</db:title>
<db:para>The examplefiles argument lists the files that are part of an example project. The optional second argument is a regular expression; if provided, only the files whose path matches with the regular expression are listed.</db:para>
<db:para>The examplefiles argument can be only used within example documentation (see <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#example-command">\example</db:link>), and is typically used together with the <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#noautolist-command">\noautolist</db:link> command.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="exampleimages-op-op-regular-expression-op-op">
<db:title>exampleimages [regular_expression]</db:title>
<db:para>The exampleimages argument lists the images that are part of an example project. The optional second argument is a regular expression; if provided, only the image files whose path matches with the regular expression are listed.</db:para>
<db:para>The exampleimages argument can be only used within example documentation (see <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#example-command">\example</db:link>), and is typically used together with the <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#noautolist-command">\noautolist</db:link> command.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="functionindex">
<db:title>functionindex</db:title>
<db:para>The functionindex argument provides a complete alphabetical list of all the documented member functions. It is normally used only to generate the <db:emphasis>Qt function index</db:emphasis> page this way:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \page functions.html
    \title All Functions
    \ingroup funclists

    \brief All documented Qt functions listed alphabetically with a
    link to where each one is declared.

    This is the list of all documented member functions and global
    functions in the Qt API. Each function has a link to the
    class or header file where it is declared and documented.

    \generatelist functionindex
* /
</db:programlisting>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="legalese">
<db:title>legalese</db:title>
<db:para>The legalese argument tells QDoc to generate a list of licenses in the current documentation project. Each license is identified using the <db:link xlink:href="11-qdoc-commands-specialcontent.xml#legalese-command">\legalese</db:link> command.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="overviews">
<db:title>overviews</db:title>
<db:para>The overviews argument is used to tell QDoc to generate a list by concatenating the contents of all the <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#group-command">\group</db:link> pages. Qt uses it to generate the <db:emphasis>overviews</db:emphasis> page this way:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \page overviews.html

    \title All Overviews and HOWTOs

    \generatelist overviews
* /
</db:programlisting>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="attributions">
<db:title>attributions</db:title>
<db:para>The attributions argument is used to tell QDoc to generate a list of attributions in the documentation.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="related">
<db:title>related</db:title>
<db:para>The related argument is used in combination with the <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#group-command">\group</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="19-qdoc-commands-grouping.xml#ingroup-command">\ingroup</db:link> commands to list all the overviews related to a specified group. For example, the page for the <db:emphasis>Programming with Qt</db:emphasis> page is generated this way:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \group qt-basic-concepts
    \title Programming with Qt

    \brief The basic architecture of the Qt cross-platform application and UI framework.

    Qt is a cross-platform application and UI framework for
    writing web-enabled applications for desktop, mobile, and
    embedded operating systems. This page contains links to
    articles and overviews explaining key components and
    techniuqes used in Qt development.

    \generatelist {related}
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Each page listed on this group page contains the command:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">\ingroup qt-basic-concepts
</db:programlisting>
<db:anchor xml:id="if-command"/>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="if">
<db:title>\if</db:title>
<db:para>The \if command and the corresponding \endif command enclose parts of a QDoc comment that only will be included if the condition specified by the command's argument is true.</db:para>
<db:para>The command reads the rest of the line and parses it as an C++ #if statement.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \if defined(opensourceedition)

    \note This edition is for the development of
    \l{Qt Open Source Edition} {Free and Open Source}
    software only; see \l{Qt Commercial Editions}.

    \endif
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>This QDoc comment will only be rendered if the opensourceedition preprocessor symbol is defined, and specified in the <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#defines-variable">defines</db:link> variable in the configuration file to make QDoc process the code within #ifdef and #endif:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">defines = opensourceedition
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>You can also define the preprocessor symbol manually on the command line. For more information see the documentation of the <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#defines-variable">defines</db:link> variable.</db:para>
<db:para>See also <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#endif-command">\endif</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#else-command">\else</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#defines-variable">defines</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#falsehoods-variable">falsehoods</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="endif-command"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="endif">
<db:title>\endif</db:title>
<db:para>The \endif command and the corresponding \if command enclose parts of a QDoc comment that will be included if the condition specified by the <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#if-command">\if</db:link> command's argument is true.</db:para>
<db:para>For more information, see the documentation of the <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#if-command">\if</db:link> command.</db:para>
<db:para>See also <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#if-command">\if</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#else-command">\else</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#defines-variable">defines</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#falsehoods-variable">falsehoods</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="else-command"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="else">
<db:title>\else</db:title>
<db:para>The \else command specifies an alternative if the condition in the <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#if-command">\if</db:link> command is false.</db:para>
<db:para>The \else command can only be used within <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#if-command">\if...\endif</db:link> commands, but is useful when there is only two alternatives.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="include-command"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="include">
<db:title>\include</db:title>
<db:para>The \include command sends all or part of the file specified by its first argument to the QDoc input stream to be processed as a QDoc comment snippet.</db:para>
<db:para>The command is useful when some snippet of commands or text is to be used in multiple places in the documentation. Use the \include command wherever you want to insert a snippet into the documentation. The file containing the snippet to include, must be located under the path(s) listed in the <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#sourcedirs-variable">sourcedirs</db:link> or <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#exampledirs-variable">exampledirs</db:link> QDoc configuration variable. It can be either any source file parsed by QDoc (or even the same one where \include command is used), or any other text file. To store snippets in a separate file that is not meant to be parsed by QDoc, use a file extension that is not listed in <db:link xlink:href="22-qdoc-configuration-generalvariables.xml#sources-fileextensions-variable">sources.fileextensions</db:link>; for example, .qdocinc.</db:para>
<db:para>The command can have either one or two arguments. The first argument is always a file name. The contents of the file must be QDoc input, in other words, a sequence of QDoc commands and text, but without the enclosing QDoc comment /*! ... */ delimiters. If you want to include the entire named file, don't use the second argument. If you want to include only part of the file, see the <db:link xlink:href="12-0-qdoc-commands-miscellaneous.xml#2-argument-form">two argument form</db:link> below. Here is an example of the one argument form:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \page corefeatures.html
    \title Core Features

    \include examples/signalandslots.qdocinc
    \include examples/objectmodel.qdocinc
    \include examples/layoutmanagement.qdocinc
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>QDoc renders this page <db:link xlink:href="corefeatures.xml">as shown here</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="A2-argument-form"/>
<db:section xml:id="include-filename-snippet-identifier">
<db:title>\include filename snippet-identifier</db:title>
<db:para>It is a waste of time to make a separate .qdocinc file for every QDoc include snippet you want to use in multiple places in the documentation, especially given that you probably have to put the copyright/license notice in every one of these files. So if you have a large number of snippets to be included, you can put them all in a single file if you want, and surround each one with:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">    //! [snippet-id1]

       QDoc commands and text...

//! [snippet-id1]

    //! [snippet-id2]

       More QDoc commands and text...

//! [snippet-id2]
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Then you can use the two-argument form of the command:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">\input examples/signalandslots.qdocinc snippet-id2
\input examples/objectmodel.qdocinc another-snippet-id
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>It works as expected. The sequence of QDoc commands and text found between the two tags with the same name as the second argument is sent to the QDoc input stream. You can even have nested snippets.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Snippet identifiers work also within documentation comment (/*! .. */) blocks, so it's not necessary to use a separate .qdocinc file. When processing a comment block, QDoc removes any //! comment lines from the generated output.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:anchor xml:id="meta-command"/>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="meta">
<db:title>\meta</db:title>
<db:para>The \meta command is mainly used for including metadata in DITA XML files. It is also used for adding metadata to example documentation, and when generating HTML output for specifying the <db:emphasis>maintainer(s)</db:emphasis> of a C++ class.</db:para>
<db:para>The command has two arguments: the first argument is the name of the metadata attribute, and the second argument is the value for the attribute. Each argument should be enclosed in curly brackets, as shown in this example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \class QWidget
    \brief The QWidget class is the base class of all user interface objects.

    \ingroup basicwidgets

    \meta {technology} {User Interface}
    \meta {platform} {macOS 10.6}
    \meta {platform} {MeeGo}
    \meta {audience} {user}
    \meta {audience} {programmer}
    \meta {audience} {designer}
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>When running QDoc to generate HTML, the example above will have no effect on the generated output, but if you run QDoc to generate DITA XML, the example will generate the following:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">&amp;lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE cxxClass PUBLIC &quot;-//NOKIA//DTD DITA C++ API Class Reference Type v0.6.0//EN&quot; &quot;dtd/cxxClass.dtd&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;!--qwidget.cpp--&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;cxxClass id=&quot;id-9a14268e-6b09-4eee-b940-21a00a0961df&quot;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;apiName&amp;gt;QWidget&amp;lt;/apiName&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;shortdesc&amp;gt;the QWidget class is the base class of all user interface objects.&amp;lt;/shortdesc&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;prolog&amp;gt;
       &amp;lt;author&amp;gt;Qt Development Frameworks&amp;lt;/author&amp;gt;
       &amp;lt;publisher&amp;gt;Qt Project&amp;lt;/publisher&amp;gt;
       &amp;lt;copyright&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;copyryear year=&quot;2020&quot;/&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;copyrholder&amp;gt;Qt Project&amp;lt;/copyrholder&amp;gt;
       &amp;lt;/copyright&amp;gt;
       &amp;lt;permissions view=&quot;all&quot;/&amp;gt;
       &amp;lt;metadata&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;audience type=&quot;designer&quot;/&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;audience type=&quot;programmer&quot;/&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;audience type=&quot;user&quot;/&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;category&amp;gt;Class reference&amp;lt;/category&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;prodinfo&amp;gt;
               &amp;lt;prodname&amp;gt;Qt Reference Documentation&amp;lt;/prodname&amp;gt;
               &amp;lt;vrmlist&amp;gt;
                   &amp;lt;vrm version=&quot;4&quot; release=&quot;7&quot; modification=&quot;3&quot;/&amp;gt;
               &amp;lt;/vrmlist&amp;gt;
               &amp;lt;component&amp;gt;QtGui&amp;lt;/component&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;/prodinfo&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;othermeta name=&quot;platform&quot; content=&quot;MeeGo&quot;/&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;othermeta name=&quot;platform&quot; content=&quot;macOS 10.6&quot;/&amp;gt;
           &amp;lt;othermeta name=&quot;technology&quot; content=&quot;User Interface&quot;/&amp;gt;
       &amp;lt;/metadata&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;/prolog&amp;gt;
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>In the example output, several values have been set using default values obtained from the QDoc configuration file. See <db:link xlink:href="21-3-qt-dita-xml-output.xml">Generating DITA XML Output</db:link> for details.</db:para>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">Example Metadata</db:emphasis></db:para>
<db:para>Another use for \meta command is to include metadata (tags) in <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#example-command">\example</db:link> documentation. By default, QDoc generates example tags based on the example's <db:link xlink:href="20-qdoc-commands-namingthings.xml#title-command">\title</db:link> and module name. These tags are displayed in Qt Creator's Welcome mode, helping users navigate the list of examples.</db:para>
<db:para>Additional tags can be created with \\meta {tag} {tag1,[tag2,...]}. For example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">/ *!
    \example helloworld
    \title Hello World Example
    \meta {tag} {tutorial,basic}
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>This would result in the following tags: <db:emphasis>tutorial,basic,hello,world</db:emphasis>. Common words such as <db:emphasis>example</db:emphasis> are ignored.</db:para>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">Example Install Paths</db:emphasis></db:para>
<db:para>The \meta command combined with an argument installpath specifies the location of an installed example. This value overrides the one that is set using the examplesinstallpath configuration variable.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">/ *!
    \example helloworld
    \title Hello World Example
    \meta {installpath} {tutorials}
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>See also <db:link xlink:href="qtgui-qdocconf.xml#examplesinstallpath">examplesinstallpath</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="noautolist-command"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="noautolist">
<db:title>\noautolist</db:title>
<db:para>The \noautolist command indicates that the annotated list of C++ classes or QML types, which is automatically generated at the bottom of the C++ or QML module page should be omitted, because the classes or types have been listed manually. This command can also be used with the <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#group-command">\group</db:link> command to omit the list of group members, when they are listed manually.</db:para>
<db:para>The command must stand on its own line. See <db:link xlink:href="qtsensors-qmlmodule.xml">Qt Sensors QML Types</db:link> for an example. The page is generated from qtsensors5.qdoc. There you will find a qdoc comment containing the \qmlmodule command for the <db:link xlink:href="qtsensors-module.xml">QtSensors</db:link> module. The same qdoc comment contains two \annotated-list commands to list the QML types in two separate groups. The QML types have been divided into these two groups because it makes more sense to list them this way than it does to list them in a single alphabetical list. At the bottom of the comment, \noautolist has been used to tell qdoc not to generate the automatic annotated list.</db:para>
<db:para>This command was introduced in QDoc 5.6.</db:para>
<db:para>Since Qt 5.10, this command can be applied also to <db:link xlink:href="13-qdoc-commands-topics.xml#example-command">\example</db:link> documentation, where it causes the automatically generated list of files and images belonging to an example project to be omitted.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="omit-command"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="omit">
<db:title>\omit</db:title>
<db:para>The \omit command and the corresponding \endomit command delimit parts of the documentation that you want QDoc to skip. For example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    \table
    \row
        \li Basic Widgets
        \li Basic GUI widgets such as buttons, comboboxes
           and scrollbars.

    \omit
    \row
        \li Component Model
        \li Interfaces and helper classes for the Qt
           Component Model.
    \endomit

    \row
        \li Database Classes
        \li Database related classes, e.g. for SQL databases.
    \endtable
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>QDoc renders this as:</db:para>
<db:informaltable cellpadding="2"
                    cellspacing="1" border="0">

                <db:tr valign="top"  class="bgcolor-d0d0d0" ><?dbhtml bgcolor="d0d0d0" ?><?dbfo bgcolor="d0d0d0" ?>
                    <db:td>Basic Widgets</db:td>
                    <db:td>Basic GUI widgets such as buttons, comboboxes
                       and scrollbars.</db:td>
                </db:tr>

                <db:tr valign="top"  class="bgcolor-c0c0c0" ><?dbhtml bgcolor="c0c0c0" ?><?dbfo bgcolor="c0c0c0" ?>
                    <db:td>Database Classes</db:td>
                    <db:td>Database related classes, e.g. for SQL databases.</db:td>
                </db:tr>
                </db:informaltable>
<db:anchor xml:id="raw-command"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="raw-avoid">
<db:title>\raw (avoid)</db:title>
<db:para>The \raw command and the corresponding \endraw command delimit a block of raw mark-up language code.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Avoid using this command if possible, because it generates DITA XML code that causes problems. If you are trying to generate special table or list behavior, try to get the behavior you want using the <db:link xlink:href="04-qdoc-commands-textmarkup.xml#span-command">\span</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="04-qdoc-commands-textmarkup.xml#div-command">\div</db:link> commands in your <db:link xlink:href="10-qdoc-commands-tablesandlists.xml#table-command">\table</db:link> or <db:link xlink:href="10-qdoc-commands-tablesandlists.xml#list-command">\list</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:para>The command takes an argument specifying the code's format. Currently, the only supported format is HTML.</db:para>
<db:para>The \raw command is useful if you want some special HTML effects in your documentation.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">/ *!
    Qt has some predefined QColor objects.

    \raw HTML
    &amp;lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot; id=&quot;colorstyles&quot;&amp;gt;
    #color-blue { background-color: #0000ff; color: #ffffff }
    #color-darkBlue { background-color: #000080; color: #ffffff }
    #color-cyan { background-color: #00ffff; color: #000000 }
    &amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;tt id=&quot;color-blue&quot;&amp;gt;Blue(#0000ff)&amp;lt;/tt&amp;gt;,
    &amp;lt;tt id=&quot;color-darkBlue&quot;&amp;gt;dark blue(#000080)&amp;lt;/tt&amp;gt; and
    &amp;lt;tt id=&quot;color-cyan&quot;&amp;gt;cyan(#00ffff)&amp;lt;/tt&amp;gt;.
&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    \endraw
* /
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>QDoc renders this as:</db:para>
<db:blockquote><db:para>Qt has some predefined QColor objects.</db:para>
<db:programlisting role="raw-html"><![CDATA[               <style type="text/css" id="colorstyles">
               #color-blue { background-color: #0000ff; color: #ffffff }
               #color-darkBlue { background-color: #000080; color: #ffffff }
               #color-cyan { background-color: #00ffff; color: #000000 }
               </style>

               <p>
               <tt id="color-blue">Blue(#0000ff)</tt>,
               <tt id="color-darkBlue">dark blue(#000080)</tt> and
               <tt id="color-cyan">cyan(#00ffff)</tt>.
           </p>
               ]]></db:programlisting>
</db:blockquote>
<db:note>
<db:para>But you can achieve the exact same thing using qdoc commands. In this case, all you have to do is include the color styles in your style.css file. Then you can write:</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">\tt {\span {id=&quot;color-blue&quot;} {Blue(#0000ff)}},
\tt {\span {id=&quot;color-darkBlue&quot;} {dark blue(#000080)}} and
\tt {\span {id=&quot;color-cyan&quot;} {cyan(#00ffff)}}.
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>...which is rendered as:</db:para>
<db:para><db:code>Blue(#0000ff)</db:code>, <db:code>dark blue(#000080)</db:code> and <db:code>cyan(#00ffff)</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="unicode-command"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="unicode">
<db:title>\unicode</db:title>
<db:para>The \unicode command allows you to insert an arbitrary Unicode character in the document.</db:para>
<db:para>The command takes an argument specifying the character as an integer. By default, base 10 is assumed, unless a '0x' or '0' prefix is specified (for base 16 and 8, respectively). For example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">O G\unicode{0xEA}nio e as Rosas

\unicode 0xC0 table en famille avec 15 \unicode 0x20AC par jour

\unicode 0x3A3 \e{a}\sub{\e{i}}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>QDoc renders this as:</db:para>
<db:blockquote><db:para>O Gênio e as Rosas</db:para>
<db:para>À table en famille avec 15 € par jour</db:para>
<db:para>Σ <db:emphasis>a</db:emphasis><db:subscript><db:emphasis>i</db:emphasis></db:subscript></db:para>
</db:blockquote>
</db:section>
</db:article>
