<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Publishing to Google Play</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.14.2 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Provides instructions to prepare your application for publishing.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="android.xml">Qt for Android</db:link> provides a complete solution to develop, build, and package your applications for Android. Most of these tasks, especially packaging and deployment are handled by Qt Creator providing rich developer experience.</db:para>
<db:para>Every time you run the application using Qt Creator, an Android Application Package (APK) is created and deployed onto the target (device or emulator) you choose. With some minor changes to how the <db:emphasis>.apk</db:emphasis> is created, you can publish your application on Google Play and monetize. The following step-by-step instructions guide you to create an <db:emphasis>.apk</db:emphasis> that can go live on Google Play:</db:para>
<db:orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Open your application project using Qt Creator v3.0 or later and change its <db:guilabel>Build</db:guilabel> settings to build release version.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Select <db:guilabel>Create Templates</db:guilabel> under <db:guilabel>Build</db:guilabel> settings to create the template files such as <db:emphasis>AndroidManifest.xml</db:emphasis> and other resources.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>You can edit the <db:emphasis>AndroidManifest.xml</db:emphasis> in <db:guilabel>General</db:guilabel> or <db:guilabel>XML Source</db:guilabel> mode.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Check for the following in <db:emphasis>AndroidManifest.xml</db:emphasis>:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:guilabel>Minimum required SDK</db:guilabel> is set to API 9 or later.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Qt Quick Controls with native <db:link xlink:href="qtquickcontrols-platformnotes.xml#android-style">Android style</db:link> require API 11 (Android v3.0) or later.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Add <db:guilabel>Application name</db:guilabel> and <db:guilabel>Application icon</db:guilabel>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:guilabel>Permissions</db:guilabel> list has all the required permissions.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:guilabel>Features</db:guilabel> list has the software or hardware features that your application depends on. For example, NFC.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:note>
<db:para>Qt adds the default permissions and features based on the module dependencies of your application. If you do not want these default permissions and features, remove the &lt;!-- %%INSERT_PERMISSIONS --&gt; and &lt;!-- %%INSERT_FEATURES --&gt; comments from <db:emphasis>AndroidManifest.xml</db:emphasis>. For information on the manifest XML format, see <db:link xlink:href="http://developer.android.com/guide/topics/manifest/manifest-intro.html">Android: App Manifest</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Set up a <db:guilabel>keystore</db:guilabel> to sign the <db:emphasis>.apk</db:emphasis>. You can create a new keystore if you do not have one. For more details, see <db:link xlink:href="http://doc.qt.io/qtcreator/creator-deploying-android.html#specifying-settings-for-packages">QtCreator: Specifying Settings for Packages</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Select <db:guilabel>Open package location after build</db:guilabel> and run your application to build the <db:emphasis>.apk</db:emphasis>. Qt Creator builds the <db:emphasis>.apk</db:emphasis> and opens the folder containing the <db:emphasis>.apk</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Log in to the <db:link xlink:href="https://play.google.com/apps/publish">Google Play Developer Console</db:link> and upload the <db:emphasis>.apk</db:emphasis> file, few screen captures of the application, and a description.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:orderedlist>
<db:para>Now your application is available to other Android device users via Google Play. You can also choose to publish the application to a smaller group, so that you can test and improve the application before publishing it to a larger audience.</db:para>
<db:para>See <db:link xlink:href="deployment-android.xml">Deploying an Application on Android</db:link> for more information about how the packaging is done and how you can influence it.</db:para>
</db:article>
