<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Android GNU C++ Run-time Licensing</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.3.2 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="android-platform-notes.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="prev" xlink:title="Android Platform Notes"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="android.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="next" xlink:title="Qt for Android"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Provides additional information about the licensing of run-time dependencies of Qt for Android.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>The Android platform does not provide a full implementation of the C++ run-time. Instead, apps that depend on features such as STL, exceptions, or RTTI, must include an additional native run-time library that provides the features they need.</db:para>
<db:para>When built with g++, Qt will use the GNU libstdc++ library which is distributed as part of the Google Android NDK. Qt Creator will copy this library into the .APK for any Qt-based Android app. The library will then be loaded by the app on start-up to meet the run-time requirements of Qt.The GNU C++ run-time is licensed under the <db:link xlink:href="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/libstdc++/manual/appendix_gpl.html">GNU General Public License version 3</db:link> with an exception which grants permission for run-time linking and usage of the library by an application which would otherwise violate the terms of the main license. For more information about this exception, see <db:link xlink:href="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/libstdc++/manual/license.html">the official license page</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:para>When Qt is built with clang instead, it will use LLVM's libc++, which is dual-licensed under both the University of Illinois &quot;BSD-Like&quot; license and the MIT license.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="information-about-the-gnu-c-run-time-license-from-gcc-headers">
<db:title>Information About The GNU C++ Run-time License From GCC Headers</db:title>
<db:para>This file is part of the GNU ISO C++ Library. This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 3, or (at your option) any later version.</db:para>
<db:para>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for more details.</db:para>
<db:para>Under Section 7 of GPL version 3, you are granted additional permissions described in the GCC Runtime Library Exception, version 3.1, as published by the Free Software Foundation.</db:para>
<db:para>You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License and a copy of the GCC Runtime Library Exception along with this program; see the files COPYING3 and COPYING.RUNTIME respectively. If not, see &lt;http://www.gnu.org/licenses/&gt;.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="the-gcc-run-time-library-exception">
<db:title>The GCC Run-time Library Exception</db:title>
<db:para>GCC RUNTIME LIBRARY EXCEPTION</db:para>
<db:para>Version 3.1, 31 March 2009</db:para>
<db:para>Copyright (C) 2009 Free Software Foundation, Inc.</db:para>
<db:para>Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.</db:para>
<db:para>This GCC Runtime Library Exception (&quot;Exception&quot;) is an additional permission under section 7 of the GNU General Public License, version 3 (&quot;GPLv3&quot;). It applies to a given file (the &quot;Runtime Library&quot;) that bears a notice placed by the copyright holder of the file stating that the file is governed by GPLv3 along with this Exception.</db:para>
<db:para>When you use GCC to compile a program, GCC may combine portions of certain GCC header files and runtime libraries with the compiled program. The purpose of this Exception is to allow compilation of non-GPL (including proprietary) programs to use, in this way, the header files and runtime libraries covered by this Exception.</db:para>
<db:para>0. Definitions.</db:para>
<db:para>A file is an &quot;Independent Module&quot; if it either requires the Runtime Library for execution after a Compilation Process, or makes use of an interface provided by the Runtime Library, but is not otherwise based on the Runtime Library.</db:para>
<db:para>&quot;GCC&quot; means a version of the GNU Compiler Collection, with or without modifications, governed by version 3 (or a specified later version) of the GNU General Public License (GPL) with the option of using any subsequent versions published by the FSF.</db:para>
<db:para>&quot;GPL-compatible Software&quot; is software whose conditions of propagation, modification and use would permit combination with GCC in accord with the license of GCC.</db:para>
<db:para>&quot;Target Code&quot; refers to output from any compiler for a real or virtual target processor architecture, in executable form or suitable for input to an assembler, loader, linker and/or execution phase. Notwithstanding that, Target Code does not include data in any format that is used as a compiler intermediate representation, or used for producing a compiler intermediate representation.</db:para>
<db:para>The &quot;Compilation Process&quot; transforms code entirely represented in non-intermediate languages designed for human-written code, and/or in Java Virtual Machine byte code, into Target Code. Thus, for example, use of source code generators and preprocessors need not be considered part of the Compilation Process, since the Compilation Process can be understood as starting with the output of the generators or preprocessors.</db:para>
<db:para>A Compilation Process is &quot;Eligible&quot; if it is done using GCC, alone or with other GPL-compatible software, or if it is done without using any work based on GCC. For example, using non-GPL-compatible Software to optimize any GCC intermediate representations would not qualify as an Eligible Compilation Process.</db:para>
<db:para>1. Grant of Additional Permission.</db:para>
<db:para>You have permission to propagate a work of Target Code formed by combining the Runtime Library with Independent Modules, even if such propagation would otherwise violate the terms of GPLv3, provided that all Target Code was generated by Eligible Compilation Processes. You may then convey such a combination under terms of your choice, consistent with the licensing of the Independent Modules.</db:para>
<db:para>2. No Weakening of GCC Copyleft.</db:para>
<db:para>The availability of this Exception does not imply any general presumption that third-party software is unaffected by the copyleft requirements of the license of GCC.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="information-about-the-llvm-c-run-time-license">
<db:title>Information About The LLVM C++ Run-time License</db:title>
<db:para>============================================================================== libc++ License ==============================================================================</db:para>
<db:para>The libc++ library is dual licensed under both the University of Illinois &quot;BSD-Like&quot; license and the MIT license. As a user of this code you may choose to use it under either license. As a contributor, you agree to allow your code to be used under both.</db:para>
<db:para>Full text of the relevant licenses is included below.</db:para>
<db:para>==============================================================================</db:para>
<db:para>University of Illinois/NCSA Open Source License</db:para>
<db:para>Copyright (c) 2009-2017 by the contributors listed in CREDITS.TXT</db:para>
<db:para>All rights reserved.</db:para>
<db:para>Developed by:</db:para>
<db:para>LLVM Team</db:para>
<db:para>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</db:para>
<db:para>http://llvm.org</db:para>
<db:para>Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation files (the &quot;Software&quot;), to deal with the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:</db:para>
<db:para>* Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimers.</db:para>
<db:para>* Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimers in the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</db:para>
<db:para>* Neither the names of the LLVM Team, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, nor the names of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from this Software without specific prior written permission.</db:para>
<db:para>THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &quot;AS IS&quot;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE CONTRIBUTORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS WITH THE SOFTWARE.</db:para>
<db:para>==============================================================================</db:para>
<db:para>Copyright (c) 2009-2014 by the contributors listed in CREDITS.TXT</db:para>
<db:para>Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation files (the &quot;Software&quot;), to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:</db:para>
<db:para>The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.</db:para>
<db:para>THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &quot;AS IS&quot;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
