<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>QT_ANDROID_PACKAGE_NAME</db:title>
<db:productname>QtCore</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.8.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Core Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>The app's package name.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:anchor xml:id="cmake-target-property-qt-android-package-name"/>
<db:para>The app's package name.</db:para>
<db:para>This property was introduced in Qt 6.8.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>This property is used only if targeting the Android platform.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:para>Specifies the app's package name. This is usually a unique dot separated name for the app, that will be used to identify the app on devices or in the Play Store. For example, &quot;org.qtproject.gallery&quot;.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">set_target_properties(${target} PROPERTIES
    QT_ANDROID_PACKAGE_NAME &quot;org.qtproject.gallery&quot;
)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The package name set by this property is passed to the build.gradle file as a namespace property, instead of AndroidManifest.xml, since the latter is deprecated since Android Gradle Plugin 7.4.</db:para>
<db:para>The package name considers some words or characters as illegal and the build will clean such names if any is encountered. An underscore (_) either replaces illegal characters or is appended to illegal words.</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Allowed characters: alphanumeric, an underscore or a dot [a-zA-Z0-9_.].</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Illegal words: abstract, continue, for, new, switch, assert, default, if, package, synchronized, boolean, do, goto, private, this, break, double, implements, protected, throw, byte, else, import, public, throws, case, enum, instanceof, return, transient, catch, extends, int, short, try, char, final, interface, static, void, class, finally, long, strictfp, volatile, const, float, native, super, while.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>The default package name for Qt for Android apps is org.qtproject.example.&lt;target_name&gt;.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Setting the package name manually in build.gradle (via namespace property) takes precedence over AndroidManifest.xml (via package attribute), and the latter also takes precedence over this property.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:para>For more information, see Android's <db:link xlink:href="https://developer.android.com/build/configure-app-module">configure the app module</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:section>
<db:title>See Also</db:title>
<db:para><db:emphasis>See also </db:emphasis>
<db:simplelist type="vert" role="see-also">
<db:member><db:link xlink:href="qt-android-generate-deployment-settings.xml">qt_android_generate_deployment_settings()</db:link></db:member>
</db:simplelist>
</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
