<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt Configure Options</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.4.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Configuring Qt's compile options.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-01-26</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-01-26</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">configure</db:emphasis> is a command-line tool that supports you in building a custom version of Qt from source. It's part of the main Qt source directory.</db:para>
<db:para>Since Qt 6, configure is a wrapper around <db:emphasis role="bold">cmake</db:emphasis>. CMake can also be invoked directly. configure provides additional error checking and compatibility with Qt 5.</db:para>
<db:para>This page discusses some of the configure options. For the full list of options, enter the command <db:emphasis role="bold">configure -h</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Unless stated otherwise, the commands on this page are for the Linux platforms. On macOS and Windows, the PATH and directory structure are different, therefore the commands will vary. Also, on Windows systems, the configure script is called configure.bat.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:section xml:id="configure-workflow">
<db:title>Configure Workflow</db:title>
<db:para>configure must be called in a working build environment where CMake, compilers, and required build tools are readily available. <db:link xlink:href="build-sources.xml">Building Qt Sources</db:link> lists such dependencies per platform.</db:para>
<db:para>After setting up such an environment, the typical workflow is to create a separate build directory, and then first run configure, then build Qt, and then install Qt:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">~/qt-source/configure
cmake --build . --parallel
cmake --install .
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>You might want to experiment with different configure flags, and therefore run configure multiple times. Note that CMake caches configure options and information about the environment in a file called CMakeCache.txt. Delete this file when you want to start over without cached information.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="source-build-and-install-directories">
<db:title>Source, Build, and Install Directories</db:title>
<db:para>The <db:emphasis>source</db:emphasis> directory contains the source code that is obtained from the source package or git repository. The <db:emphasis>build</db:emphasis> directory is where the build-related files, such as build system files, object files, and other intermediate files are stored. The <db:emphasis>install</db:emphasis> directory is where the binaries and libraries are installed, for use either by the system or by the application.</db:para>
<db:para>It's recommended to keep these directories separate by shadow-building and using the <db:emphasis role="bold">-prefix</db:emphasis> option. This enables you to keep the Qt <db:emphasis>source</db:emphasis> tree clean from the build artifacts and binaries, which are stored in a separate directory. This method is very convenient if you want to have multiple builds from the same source tree, but for different configurations. To shadow-build, run configure from a separate directory:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">mkdir ~/qt-build
cd ~/qt-build
~/qt-source/configure -prefix /opt/Qt6
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Configuring with the -prefix option means that the Qt binaries and libraries are installed into another directory, which is /opt/Qt6 in this case.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="examples-tests-and-tools">
<db:title>Examples, Tests, and Tools</db:title>
<db:para>By default, configure only configures Qt's libraries and tools. You can use <db:emphasis role="bold">-make examples</db:emphasis> or <db:emphasis role="bold">-make tests</db:emphasis> to also build the examples or tests that come with Qt:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">~/qt-source/configure -make examples -make tests
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>You can also configure Qt such that examples, tests, and tools are configured, but not built by default. If you set the CMake variables <db:emphasis role="bold">QT_BUILD_EXAMPLES_BY_DEFAULT</db:emphasis>, <db:emphasis role="bold">QT_BUILD_TESTS_BY_DEFAULT</db:emphasis>, and <db:emphasis role="bold">QT_BUILD_TOOLS_BY_DEFAULT</db:emphasis> to OFF, the respective parts will not be built by &quot;cmake –build .&quot;. Instead, CMake will generate individual targets that you can then build individually.</db:para>
<db:para>Here we build Qt libraries and tools, but also the <db:link xlink:href="qtwidgets-tutorials-notepad-example.xml">NotePad Example</db:link>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">~/qt-source/configure -make examples -- -D QT_NO_MAKE_EXAMPLES=ON
cmake --build . --parallel
cmake --build . --parallel --target notepad
</db:programlisting>
<db:note>
<db:para>The -developer-build option builds tests by default. See also <db:link xlink:href="configure-options.xml#developer-builds">Developer Builds</db:link> below.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="build-configurations">
<db:title>Build Configurations</db:title>
<db:para>You can build Qt libraries and tools in various variants, each of them optimized for a different use case.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="debug-and-release-builds">
<db:title>Debug and Release Builds</db:title>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-release</db:emphasis> tells the compiler to optimize the code, and not provide additional debug symbols alongside Qt and its tools.</db:para>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-debug</db:emphasis> skips some optimizations to make it easier to debug Qt and its tools. This option also enables the generation of debug symbols that let you inspect the code and state of the built libraries in a debugger.</db:para>
<db:para>Finally, <db:emphasis role="bold">-debug-and-release</db:emphasis> lets you build both a debug and release variant of Qt libraries in one go. This is only supported if you configure a build for Windows.</db:para>
<db:para>There are further options to tweak the configurations:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-force-debug-info</db:emphasis>: Creates a release build with debug information.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-separate-debug-info</db:emphasis>: Extracts the debug information into a separate file.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-optimize-size</db:emphasis>: Optimizes release builds for size instead of speed.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="static-and-shared-builds">
<db:title>Static and Shared Builds</db:title>
<db:para>Qt Modules can be built as separate libraries that an executable links to and loads at start time (for Qt libraries), or runtime (for Qt plugins). This is called a <db:emphasis>shared</db:emphasis> build and is the default configuration on most platforms. The matching configure option is <db:emphasis role="bold">-dynamic</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
<db:para>You can also build Qt such that an executable binary will include all Qt modules it links to and all Qt plugins it needs. This is called a <db:emphasis>static</db:emphasis> build and can be selected when configuring with the <db:emphasis role="bold">-static</db:emphasis> option.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="cmake-generators">
<db:title>CMake Generators</db:title>
<db:para>When configuring, you can select a CMake generator. Note that CMake supports generators that cannot be used with Qt. Therefore, configure automatically selects a generator for you.</db:para>
<db:para>configure always uses the <db:emphasis role="bold">Ninja</db:emphasis> generator and build tool if a ninja executable is available. Ninja is both cross-platform, feature-rich, and performant, and recommended on all platforms. Use of other generators might work, but is not officially supported.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="modules-and-features">
<db:title>Modules and Features</db:title>
<db:para>Qt consists of different <db:link xlink:href="qtmodules.xml">modules</db:link> whose sources can be found in different directories inside the top-level source directory. Users can explicitly exclude specific top-level directories to limit build times. Furthermore, each Qt module might have features that can also be explicitly enabled or disabled.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="excluding-qt-modules">
<db:title>Excluding Qt Modules</db:title>
<db:para><db:code>configure</db:code>'s <db:emphasis role="bold">-skip</db:emphasis> option allows top-level source directories to be excluded from the Qt build. Note that some directories contain multiple Qt modules. For example, to exclude the Qt Wayland Compositor and the Qt Wayland integration plugin from the Qt build, provide <db:emphasis role="bold">-skip qtwayland</db:emphasis> as an option to configure.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">~/qt-source/configure -skip qtwayland
</db:programlisting>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="including-or-excluding-features">
<db:title>Including or Excluding Features</db:title>
<db:para>The <db:emphasis role="bold">-feature-</db:emphasis><db:emphasis>&lt;feature&gt;</db:emphasis> and <db:emphasis role="bold">-no-feature-</db:emphasis><db:emphasis>&lt;feature&gt;</db:emphasis> options include and exclude specific features, respectively.</db:para>
<db:para>For example, you can use the <db:emphasis role="bold">-no-feature-accessibility</db:emphasis> configure option to disable <db:link xlink:href="accessible.xml">Accessibility</db:link> support in Qt:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">~/qt-source/configure -no-feature-accessibility
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Use <db:emphasis role="bold">configure -list-features</db:emphasis> to show a list of all available features on the command line. Note that features can depend on other features, so disabling a feature might have side-effects on other features.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="third-party-libraries">
<db:title>Third-Party Libraries</db:title>
<db:para>The Qt source packages include third-party libraries. To set whether Qt should use the system's versions of the libraries or to use the bundled version, pass either <db:emphasis role="bold">-system</db:emphasis> or <db:emphasis role="bold">-qt</db:emphasis> before the name of the library to configure.</db:para>
<db:para>The table below summarizes some third-party options:</db:para>
<db:informaltable style="generic">
<db:thead>
<db:tr>
<db:th>
<db:para>Library Name</db:para>
</db:th>
<db:th>
<db:para>Bundled in Qt</db:para>
</db:th>
<db:th>
<db:para>Installed in System</db:para>
</db:th>
</db:tr>
</db:thead>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>zlib</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-qt-zlib</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-system-zlib</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>libjpeg</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-qt-libjpeg</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-system-libjpeg</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>libpng</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-qt-libpng</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-system-libpng</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>freetype</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-qt-freetype</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-system-freetype</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>PCRE</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-qt-pcre</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-system-pcre</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>HarfBuzz-NG</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-qt-harfbuzz</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-system-harfbuzz</db:emphasis></db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
</db:informaltable>
<db:para>It's also possible to disable support for these libraries by using <db:emphasis role="bold">-no</db:emphasis> instead of <db:emphasis role="bold">-qt</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
<db:para>configure in Qt 6 relies on CMake to locate third-party libraries. It does so by checking various system paths. If you installed libraries somewhere else, you can let CMake know this by setting or extending the <db:emphasis role="bold">CMAKE_PREFIX_PATH</db:emphasis> variable.</db:para>
<db:para>For a full list of options, consult the help with <db:emphasis role="bold">configure -help</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="ssl">
<db:title>SSL</db:title>
<db:para>Qt Network can be configured to support communication for Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) but does not implement the actual algorithms itself. It needs to leverage other libraries instead.</db:para>
<db:para>On Windows, Qt can use the system's Secure Channel library for this purpose (configure option <db:emphasis role="bold">-schannel</db:emphasis>). On macOS and iOS, Qt can be configured to use the SecureTransport API (configure option <db:emphasis role="bold">-securetransport</db:emphasis>).</db:para>
<db:para>The most feature-complete support that also works on almost all target platforms is provided by the <db:link xlink:href="http://www.openssl.org/">OpenSSL Toolkit</db:link> (option <db:emphasis role="bold">-openssl</db:emphasis>). Qt does require OpenSSL 1.1.1 or later.</db:para>
<db:para>Qt can be configured to use OpenSSL in three ways:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Qt Network loads OpenSSL libraries (DLLs) when first needed, at runtime. If not found, the application continues to run but fails to handle SSL communication. This is enabled by using the configure option <db:emphasis role="bold">-openssl-runtime</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Qt Network links against the OpenSSL libraries. If they cannot be found at load time, the application fails to start. This is enabled by using the configure option <db:emphasis role="bold">-openssl-linked</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Qt Network compiles against a static version of the OpenSSL libraries, and OpenSSL becomes part of the Qt Network library. This is enabled by using the configure option <db:emphasis role="bold">openssl-linked</db:emphasis> and setting the <db:emphasis role="bold">OPENSSL_USE_STATIC_LIBS</db:emphasis> variable to <db:emphasis role="bold">ON</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>Set the CMake variable <db:emphasis role="bold">OPENSSL_ROOT_DIR</db:emphasis> if OpenSSL is not installed in a standard location, and therefore not found by configure.</db:para>
<db:para>See <db:link xlink:href="ssl.xml">Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) Classes</db:link> for further instructions on Qt with SSL support.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="cross-compilation-options">
<db:title>Cross-Compilation Options</db:title>
<db:para>To configure Qt for cross-platform development and deployment, you need to have a matching Qt version for the host machine first. Also, the development toolchain for the target platform needs to be set up. This set up varies among the <db:link xlink:href="supported-platforms.xml">Supported Platforms</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:para>Common options are:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-external-hostbindir</db:emphasis> - Path to Qt tools built for this machine.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-device</db:emphasis> - Select devices/mkspec for the qmake companion files.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">-device-option</db:emphasis> - sets additional qmake variables.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:note>
<db:para>Toolchains for non-desktop targets often come with a so-called <db:emphasis>sysroot</db:emphasis> that Qt needs to be configured against.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="developer-builds">
<db:title>Developer Builds</db:title>
<db:para>The <db:emphasis role="bold">-developer-build</db:emphasis> configure option is a convenience option that optimizes the build for developing Qt itself. It shouldn't be used for building Qt variants that ship to customers.</db:para>
<db:para>Libraries in a developer build contain more exported symbols than a standard build, and all Qt code compiles with a higher warning level. It also changes the default prefix to the build directory, avoiding the need to install Qt before testing things, and finally enables the compilation of Qt's auto-tests by default.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="specific-options-for-platforms">
<db:title>Specific Options for Platforms</db:title>
<db:para>The following pages provide guidelines on how to configure Qt for specific platform development:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="building-qt-for-qnx.xml">Building Qt for QNX</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="configure-linux-device.xml">Configure an Embedded Linux Device</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="android-building.xml">Qt for Android - Building from Source</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="linux-building.xml">Qt for Linux/X11 - Building from Source</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="windows-building.xml">Qt for Windows - Building from Source</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="macos-building.xml">Qt for macOS - Building from Source</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="integrity-monolith-project-tutorial.xml">Qt for INTEGRITY - Monolith Project Tutorial</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="ios-building-from-source.xml">Qt for iOS - Building from Source</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="wasm.xml#wasm-building-qt-from-source">Qt for WebAssembly - Building from Source</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
</db:article>
