<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Getting Started Programming with Qt Quick</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.7.1 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt Reference Documentation.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>Welcome to the world of <db:emphasis role="bold">QML</db:emphasis>, the declarative UI language. In this Getting Started guide, we will create a simple text editor application using QML. After reading this guide, you should be ready to develop your own applications using QML and Qt C++.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="qml-to-build-user-interfaces">
<db:title>QML to Build User Interfaces</db:title>
<db:para>The application we are building is a simple text editor that will load, save, and perform some text manipulation. This guide will consist of two parts. The first part will involve designing the application layout and behaviors using declarative language in QML. For the second part, file loading and saving will be implemented using Qt C++. Using <db:link xlink:href="metaobjects.xml">Qt's Meta-Object System</db:link>, we can expose C++ functions as properties that <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-typesystem-objecttypes.xml">QML object types</db:link> can use. Utilizing QML and Qt C++, we can efficiently decouple the interface logic from the application logic.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor5_editmenu.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>The complete source code is in the <db:code>examples/quick/tutorials/gettingStartedQml</db:code> directory. If you wish to see how the finalized application looks like, you can skip to chapter <db:link xlink:href="gettingstartedqml.xml#running-the-text-editor">Running the Text Editor</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:para>The C++ portion of this tutorial assumes that the reader possesses basic knowledge of Qt's compilation procedures.</db:para>
<db:para>Tutorial chapters:</db:para>
<db:orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="gettingstartedqml.xml#defining-a-button-and-a-menu">Defining a Button and a Menu</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="gettingstartedqml.xml#implementing-a-menu-bar">Implementing a Menu Bar</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="gettingstartedqml.xml#building-a-text-editor">Building a Text Editor</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="gettingstartedqml.xml#decorating-the-text-editor">Decorating the Text Editor</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="gettingstartedqml.xml#extending-qml-using-qt-c">Extending QML using Qt C++</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:orderedlist>
<db:para>Information about QML, such as syntax and features, is included in the <db:link xlink:href="qmlreference.xml">The QML Reference</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="defining-a-button-and-a-menu">
<db:title>Defining a Button and a Menu</db:title>
<db:section xml:id="basic-component-a-button">
<db:title>Basic Component - a Button</db:title>
<db:para>We start our text editor by building a button. Functionally, a button has a mouse sensitive area and a label. Buttons perform actions when a user presses the button.</db:para>
<db:para>In QML, the basic visual item is the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-rectangle.xml">Rectangle</db:link> type. The <db:code>Rectangle</db:code> <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-typesystem-objecttypes.xml">QML object type</db:link> has <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-syntax-propertybinding.xml">QML properties</db:link> to control its appearance and location.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">import QtQuick 2.3

Rectangle {
    id: simpleButton
    color: &quot;grey&quot;
    width: 150; height: 75

    Text {
        id: buttonLabel
        anchors.centerIn: parent
        text: &quot;button label&quot;
    }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>First, the <db:code>import QtQuick 2.3</db:code> statement allows the <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-qmlscene.xml">qmlscene</db:link> tool to import the QML types we will later use. This line must exist for every QML file. Notice that the version of Qt modules is included in the import statement.</db:para>
<db:para>This simple rectangle has a unique identifier, <db:code>simpleButton</db:code>, which is bound to the <db:code>id</db:code> property. The <db:code>Rectangle</db:code> object's properties are bound to values by listing the property, followed by a colon, then the value. In the code sample, the color <db:code>grey</db:code> is bound to the Rectangle's <db:code>color</db:code> property. Similarly, we bind the <db:code>width</db:code> and <db:code>height</db:code> of the Rectangle.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:link xlink:href="whatsnew50.xml#text">Text</db:link> type is a non-editable text field. We name this object <db:code>buttonLabel</db:code>. To set the string content of the Text field, we bind a value to the <db:code>text</db:code> property. The label is contained within the Rectangle and in order to center it in the middle, we assign the <db:code>anchors</db:code> of the Text object to its parent, which is called <db:code>simpleButton</db:code>. Anchors may bind to other items' anchors, allowing layout assignments simpler.</db:para>
<db:para>We shall save this code as <db:code>SimpleButton.qml</db:code>. Running <db:code>qmlscene</db:code> with the file as the argument will display the grey rectangle with a text label.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor1_simplebutton.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>To implement the button click functionality, we can use QML's event handling. QML's event handling is very similar to <db:link xlink:href="signalsandslots.xml">Qt's signal and slot</db:link> mechanism. Signals are emitted and the connected slot is called.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Rectangle {
    id: simpleButton
    ...

    MouseArea {
        id: buttonMouseArea

        // Anchor all sides of the mouse area to the rectangle's anchors
        anchors.fill: parent
        // onClicked handles valid mouse button clicks
        onClicked: console.log(buttonLabel.text + &quot; clicked&quot;)
    }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>We include a <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-mousearea.xml">MouseArea</db:link> object in our simpleButton. <db:code>MouseArea</db:code> objects describe the interactive area where mouse movements are detected. For our button, we anchor the whole <db:code>MouseArea</db:code> to its parent, which is <db:code>simpleButton</db:code>. The <db:code>anchors.fill</db:code> syntax is one way of accessing a specific property called <db:code>fill</db:code> inside a group of properties called <db:code>anchors</db:code>. QML uses <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-positioning-anchors.xml">anchor-based layouts</db:link> where items can anchor to another item, creating robust layouts.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:code>MouseArea</db:code> has many signal handlers that are called during mouse movements within the specified <db:code>MouseArea</db:code> boundaries. One of them is <db:code>onClicked</db:code> and it is called whenever the acceptable mouse button is clicked, the left click being the default. We can bind actions to the onClicked handler. In our example, <db:code>console.log()</db:code> outputs text whenever the mouse area is clicked. The function <db:code>console.log()</db:code> is a useful tool for debugging purposes and for outputting text.</db:para>
<db:para>The code in <db:code>SimpleButton.qml</db:code> is sufficient to display a button on the screen and output text whenever it is clicked with a mouse.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Rectangle {
    id: button
    ...

    property color buttonColor: &quot;lightblue&quot;
    property color onHoverColor: &quot;gold&quot;
    property color borderColor: &quot;white&quot;

    signal buttonClick()

    onButtonClick: {
        console.log(buttonLabel.text + &quot; clicked&quot;)
    }

    MouseArea{
        onClicked: buttonClick()
        hoverEnabled: true
        onEntered: parent.border.color = onHoverColor
        onExited:  parent.border.color = borderColor
    }

    // Determines the color of the button by using the conditional operator
    color: buttonMouseArea.pressed ? Qt.darker(buttonColor, 1.5) : buttonColor
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>A fully functioning button is in <db:code>Button.qml</db:code>. The code snippets in this article have some code omitted, denoted by ellipses because they were either introduced earlier in the previous sections or irrelevant to the current code discussion.</db:para>
<db:para>Custom properties are declared using the <db:code>property type name</db:code> syntax. In the code, the property <db:code>buttonColor</db:code>, of type <db:code>color</db:code>, is declared and bound to the value <db:code>&quot;lightblue&quot;</db:code>. The <db:code>buttonColor</db:code> is later used in a conditional operation to determine the button's fill color. Note that property value assignment is possible using the <db:code>=</db:code> equals sign, in addition to value binding using the <db:code>:</db:code> colon character. Custom properties allow internal items to be accessible outside of the Rectangle's scope. There are basic <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-typesystem-basictypes.xml">QML types</db:link> such as <db:code>int</db:code>, <db:code>string</db:code>, <db:code>real</db:code>, as well as a type called <db:code>variant</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:para>By binding the <db:code>onEntered</db:code> and <db:code>onExited</db:code> signal handlers to colors, the button's border will turn yellow when the mouse hovers above the button and reverts the color when the mouse exits the mouse area.</db:para>
<db:para>A <db:code>buttonClick()</db:code> signal is declared in <db:code>Button.qml</db:code> by placing the <db:code>signal</db:code> keyword in front of the signal name. All signals have their handlers automatically created, their names starting with <db:code>on</db:code>. As a result, the <db:code>onButtonClick</db:code> is <db:code>buttonClick</db:code>'s handler. The <db:code>onButtonClick</db:code> is then assigned an action to perform. In our button example, the <db:code>onClicked</db:code> mouse handler will simply call <db:code>onButtonClick</db:code>, which displays a text. The <db:code>onButtonClick</db:code> enables outside objects to access the <db:code>Button</db:code>'s mouse area easily. For example, items may have more than one <db:code>MouseArea</db:code> declarations and a <db:code>buttonClick</db:code> signal can make the distinction between the several <db:code>MouseArea</db:code> signal handlers better.</db:para>
<db:para>We now have the basic knowledge to implement items in QML that can handle basic mouse movements. We created a <db:code>Text</db:code> label inside a <db:code>Rectangle</db:code>, customized its properties, and implemented behaviors that respond to mouse movements. This idea of creating QML objects within objects is repeated throughout the text editor application.</db:para>
<db:para>This button is not useful unless used as a component to perform an action. In the next section, we will soon create a menu containing several of these buttons.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor1_button.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="creating-a-menu-page">
<db:title>Creating a Menu Page</db:title>
<db:para>Up to this stage, we covered how to create objects and assign behaviors inside a single QML file. In this section, we will cover how to import QML types and how to reuse some of the created components to build other components.</db:para>
<db:para>Menus display the contents of a list, each item having the ability to perform an action. In QML, we can create a menu in several ways. First, we will create a menu containing buttons which will eventually perform different actions. The menu code is in <db:code>FileMenu.qml</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">import QtQuick 2.3             \\ Import the main Qt QML module
import &quot;folderName&quot;            \\ import the contents of a folder
import &quot;script.js&quot; as Script   \\ Import a Javascript file and name it as Script
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The syntax shown above shows how to use the <db:code>import</db:code> keyword. This is required to use JavaScript files, or QML files that are not within the same directory. Since <db:code>Button.qml</db:code> is in the same directory as <db:code>FileMenu.qml</db:code>, we do not need to import the <db:code>Button.qml</db:code> file to use it. We can directly create a <db:code>Button</db:code> object by declaring <db:code>Button{}</db:code>, similar to a <db:code>Rectangle{}</db:code> declaration.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">In FileMenu.qml:

    Row {
        anchors.centerIn: parent
        spacing: parent.width / 6

        Button {
            id: loadButton
            buttonColor: &quot;lightgrey&quot;
            label: &quot;Load&quot;
        }
        Button {
            buttonColor: &quot;grey&quot;
            id: saveButton
            label: &quot;Save&quot;
        }
        Button {
            id: exitButton
            label: &quot;Exit&quot;
            buttonColor: &quot;darkgrey&quot;

            onButtonClick: Qt.quit()
        }
    }
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>In <db:code>FileMenu.qml</db:code>, we declare three <db:code>Button</db:code> objects. They are declared inside a <db:link xlink:href="10-qdoc-commands-tablesandlists.xml">Row</db:link> type, a positioner that will position its children along a vertical row. The <db:code>Button</db:code> declaration resides in Button.qml, which is the same as the one we used in the previous section. New property bindings can be declared within the newly created buttons, effectively overwriting the properties set in <db:code>Button.qml</db:code>. The button called <db:code>exitButton</db:code> will quit and close the window when it is clicked. Note that the signal handler <db:code>onButtonClick</db:code> in <db:code>Button.qml</db:code> will be called in addition to the <db:code>onButtonClick</db:code> handler in <db:code>exitButton</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor1_filemenu.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>The <db:code>Row</db:code> declaration is declared in a <db:code>Rectangle</db:code>, creating a rectangle container for the row of buttons. This additional rectangle creates an indirect way of organizing the row of buttons inside a menu.</db:para>
<db:para>The declaration of the edit menu is very similar at this stage. The menu has buttons that have the labels: <db:code>Copy</db:code>, <db:code>Paste</db:code>, and <db:code>Select All</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor1_editmenu.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>Armed with our knowledge of importing and customizing previously made components, we may now combine these menu pages to create a menu bar, consisting of buttons to select the menu, and look at how we may structure data using QML.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="implementing-a-menu-bar">
<db:title>Implementing a Menu Bar</db:title>
<db:para>Our text editor application will need a way to display menus using a menu bar. The menu bar will switch the different menus and the user can choose which menu to display. Menu switching implies that the menus need more structure than merely displaying them in a row. QML uses models and views to structure data and display the structured data.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="using-data-models-and-views">
<db:title>Using Data Models and Views</db:title>
<db:para>QML has different <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-modelviewsdata-modelview.xml#models">data views</db:link> that display <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-modelviewsdata-modelview.xml#models">data models</db:link>. Our menu bar will display the menus in a list, with a header that displays a row of menu names. The list of menus are declared inside a <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtqml-models-objectmodel.xml">ObjectModel</db:link>. The <db:code>ObjectModel</db:code> type contains items that already are displayable, such as <db:code>Rectangle</db:code> objects. Other model types, like the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtqml-models-listmodel.xml">ListModel</db:link> type, need a delegate to display their data.</db:para>
<db:para>We declare two visual items in the <db:code>menuListModel</db:code>, the <db:code>FileMenu</db:code> and the <db:code>EditMenu</db:code>. We customize the two menus and display them in a <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-listview.xml">ListView</db:link>. The <db:code>MenuBar.qml</db:code> file contains the QML declarations and a simple edit menu is defined in <db:code>EditMenu.qml</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">ObjectModel {
    id: menuListModel

    FileMenu {
        width: menuListView.width
        height: menuBar.height
        color: fileColor
    }

    EditMenu {
        color: editColor
        width: menuListView.width
        height: menuBar.height
    }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-listview.xml">ListView</db:link> type will display a model according to a delegate. The delegate can display the model items in a <db:code>Row</db:code> object or in a grid. Our <db:code>menuListModel</db:code> already has visible items, therefore, we do not need to declare a delegate.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">ListView {
    id: menuListView

    // Anchors are set to react to window anchors
    anchors.fill: parent
    anchors.bottom: parent.bottom
    width: parent.width
    height: parent.height

    // The model contains the data
    model: menuListModel

    // Control the movement of the menu switching
    snapMode: ListView.SnapOneItem
    orientation: ListView.Horizontal
    boundsBehavior: Flickable.StopAtBounds
    flickDeceleration: 5000
    highlightFollowsCurrentItem: true
    highlightMoveDuration: 240
    highlightRangeMode: ListView.StrictlyEnforceRange
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Additionally, <db:code>ListView</db:code> inherits from <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-flickable.xml">Flickable</db:link>, making the list respond to mouse drags and other gestures. The last portion of the code above sets <db:code>Flickable</db:code> properties to create the desired flicking movement to our view. In particular,the property <db:code>highlightMoveDuration</db:code> changes the duration of the flick transition. A higher <db:code>highlightMoveDuration</db:code> value results in slower menu switching.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:code>ListView</db:code> maintains the model items through an <db:code>index</db:code> and each visual item in the model is accessible through the <db:code>index</db:code>, in the order of the declaration. Changing the <db:code>currentIndex</db:code> effectively changes the highlighted item in the <db:code>ListView</db:code>. The header of our menu bar exemplify this effect. There are two buttons in a row, both changing the current menu when clicked. The <db:code>fileButton</db:code> changes the current menu to the file menu when clicked, the <db:code>index</db:code> being <db:code>0</db:code> because <db:code>FileMenu</db:code> is declared first in the <db:code>menuListModel</db:code>. Similarly, the <db:code>editButton</db:code> will change the current menu to the <db:code>EditMenu</db:code> when clicked.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:code>labelList</db:code> rectangle has <db:code>z</db:code> value of <db:code>1</db:code>, denoting that it is displayed at the front of the menu bar. Items with higher <db:code>z</db:code> values are displayed in front of items with lower <db:code>z</db:code> values. The default <db:code>z</db:code> value is <db:code>0</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Rectangle {
    id: labelList
    ...
    z: 1

    Row {
        anchors.centerIn: parent
        spacing: 40

        Button {
            label: &quot;File&quot;
            id: fileButton
            ...
            onButtonClick: menuListView.currentIndex = 0
        }

        Button {
            id: editButton
            label: &quot;Edit&quot;
            ...
            onButtonClick: menuListView.currentIndex = 1
        }
    }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The menu bar we just created can be flicked to access the menus or by clicking on the menu names at the top. Switching menu screens feel intuitive and responsive.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor2_menubar.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="building-a-text-editor">
<db:title>Building a Text Editor</db:title>
<db:section xml:id="declaring-a-textarea">
<db:title>Declaring a TextArea</db:title>
<db:para>Our text editor is not a text editor if it didn't contain an editable text area. QML's <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-textedit.xml">TextEdit</db:link> type allows the declaration of a multi-line editable text area. <db:code>TextEdit</db:code> is different from the <db:link xlink:href="whatsnew50.xml#text">Text</db:link> type, which doesn't allow the user to directly edit the text.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">TextEdit {
    id: textEditor
    anchors.fill: parent
    width: parent.width
    height: parent.height
    color: &quot;midnightblue&quot;
    focus: true

    wrapMode: TextEdit.Wrap

    onCursorRectangleChanged: flickArea.ensureVisible(cursorRectangle)
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The editor has its font <db:code>color</db:code> property set and <db:code>wrapMode</db:code> set to wrap the text. The <db:code>TextEdit</db:code> area is inside a flickable item that will scroll the text if the text cursor is outside the visible area. The function <db:code>ensureVisible()</db:code> will check if the cursor rectangle is outside the visible boundaries and move the text area accordingly. QML uses Javascript syntax for its scripts, and as previously mentioned, Javascript files can be imported and used within a QML file.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">function ensureVisible(r) {
    if (contentX &gt;= r.x)
        contentX = r.x;
    else if (contentX + width &lt;= r.x + r.width)
        contentX = r.x + r.width - width;
    if (contentY &gt;= r.y)
        contentY = r.y;
    else if (contentY + height &lt;= r.y + r.height)
        contentY = r.y + r.height - height;
}
</db:programlisting>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="combining-components-for-the-text-editor">
<db:title>Combining Components for the Text Editor</db:title>
<db:para>We are now ready to create the layout of our text editor using QML. The text editor has two components, the menu bar we created and the text area. QML allows us to reuse components, therefore making our code simpler, by importing components and customizing when necessary. Our text editor splits the window into two; one-third of the screen is dedicated to the menu bar and two-thirds of the screen displays the text area. The menu bar is displayed in front of any other objects.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Rectangle {
    id: screen
    width: 1000
    height: 1000

    // The screen is partitioned into the MenuBar and TextArea.
    // One-third of the screen is assigned to the MenuBar
    property int partition: height / 3

    MenuBar {
        id: menuBar
        height: partition
        width: parent.width
        z: 1
    }

    TextArea {
        id: textArea
        anchors.bottom: parent.bottom
        y: partition
        color: &quot;white&quot;
        width: parent.width
        height: partition * 2
    }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>By importing reusable components, our <db:code>TextEditor</db:code> code looks much simpler. We can then customize the main application, without worrying about properties that already have defined behaviors. Using this approach, application layouts and UI components can be created easily.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor3_texteditor.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="decorating-the-text-editor">
<db:title>Decorating the Text Editor</db:title>
<db:section xml:id="implementing-a-drawer-interface">
<db:title>Implementing a Drawer Interface</db:title>
<db:para>Our text editor looks simple and we need to decorate it. Using QML, we can declare transitions and animate our text editor. Our menu bar is occupying one-third of the screen and it would be nice to have it only appear when we want it.</db:para>
<db:para>We can add a drawer interface, that will contract or expand the menu bar when clicked. In our implementation, we have a thin rectangle that responds to mouse clicks. The <db:code>drawer</db:code>, as well as the application, has two sates: the &quot;drawer is open&quot; state and the &quot;drawer is closed&quot; state. The <db:code>drawer</db:code> item is a strip of rectangle with a small height. There is a nested <db:link xlink:href="09-qdoc-commands-includingimages.xml">Image</db:link> object declaring that an arrow icon will be centered inside the drawer. The drawer assigns a state to the whole application, with the identifier <db:code>screen</db:code>, whenever a user clicks the mouse area.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Rectangle {
    id: drawer
    height: 15

    Image {
        id: arrowIcon
        source: &quot;images/arrow.png&quot;
        anchors.horizontalCenter: parent.horizontalCenter
    }

    MouseArea {
        id: drawerMouseArea
        anchors.fill: parent

        onClicked: {
            if (screen.state == &quot;DRAWER_CLOSED&quot;)
                screen.state = &quot;DRAWER_OPEN&quot;
            else if (screen.state == &quot;DRAWER_OPEN&quot;)
                screen.state = &quot;DRAWER_CLOSED&quot;
        }
        ...
    }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>A state is simply a collection of configurations and it is declared with the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtqml-statemachine-state.xml">State</db:link> type. A list of states can be listed and bound to the <db:code>states</db:code> property. In our application, the two states are called <db:code>DRAWER_CLOSED</db:code> and <db:code>DRAWER_OPEN</db:code>. Item configurations are declared in <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-propertychanges.xml">PropertyChanges</db:link> objects. In the <db:code>DRAWER_OPEN</db:code> state, there are four items that will receive property changes. The first target, <db:code>menuBar</db:code>, will change its <db:code>y</db:code> property to <db:code>0</db:code>. Similarly, the <db:code>textArea</db:code> will lower to a new position when the state is <db:code>DRAWER_OPEN</db:code>. The <db:code>textArea</db:code>, the <db:code>drawer</db:code>, and the drawer's icon will undergo property changes to meet the current state.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">states:[
    State {
        name: &quot;DRAWER_OPEN&quot;
        PropertyChanges { target: menuBar; y: 0 }
        PropertyChanges { target: textArea; y: partition + drawer.height }
        PropertyChanges { target: drawer; y: partition }
        PropertyChanges { target: arrowIcon; rotation: 180 }
    },
    State {
        name: &quot;DRAWER_CLOSED&quot;
        PropertyChanges { target: menuBar; y: -height; }
        PropertyChanges { target: textArea; y: drawer.height; height: screen.height - drawer.height }
        PropertyChanges { target: drawer; y: 0 }
        PropertyChanges { target: arrowIcon; rotation: 0 }
    }
]
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>State changes are abrupt and needs smoother transitions. Transitions between states are defined using the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-transition.xml">Transition</db:link> type, which can then bind to the item's <db:code>transitions</db:code> property. Our text editor has a state transition whenever the state changes to either <db:code>DRAWER_OPEN</db:code> or <db:code>DRAWER_CLOSED</db:code>. Importantly, the transition needs a <db:code>from</db:code> and a <db:code>to</db:code> state but for our transitions, we can use the wild card <db:code>*</db:code> symbol to denote that the transition applies to all state changes.</db:para>
<db:para>During transitions, we can assign animations to the property changes. Our <db:code>menuBar</db:code> switches position from <db:code>y: 0</db:code> to <db:code>y: -partition</db:code> and we can animate this transition using the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-numberanimation.xml">NumberAnimation</db:link> type. We declare that the targets' properties will animate for a certain duration of time and using a certain easing curve. An easing curve controls the animation rates and interpolation behavior during state transitions. The easing curve we chose is <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-propertyanimation.xml#easing.type-prop"><db:code>Easing.OutExpo</db:code></db:link>, which slows the movement near the end of the animation. For more information, see QML's <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-statesanimations-animations.xml">animation</db:link> article.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">transitions: [
    Transition {
        to: &quot;*&quot;
        NumberAnimation { target: textArea; properties: &quot;y, height&quot;; duration: 100; easing.type:Easing.OutExpo }
        NumberAnimation { target: menuBar; properties: &quot;y&quot;; duration: 100; easing.type: Easing.OutExpo }
        NumberAnimation { target: drawer; properties: &quot;y&quot;; duration: 100; easing.type: Easing.OutExpo }
    }
]
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Another way of animating property changes is by declaring a <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-behavior.xml">Behavior</db:link> type. A transition only works during state changes and <db:code>Behavior</db:code> can set an animation for a general property change. In the text editor, the arrow has a <db:code>NumberAnimation</db:code> animating its <db:code>rotation</db:code> property whenever the property changes.</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>TextEditor.qml</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Behavior {
    NumberAnimation { property: &quot;rotation&quot;; easing.type: Easing.OutExpo }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Going back to our components with knowledge of states and animations, we can improve the appearances of the components. In <db:code>Button.qml</db:code>, we can add <db:code>color</db:code> and <db:code>scale</db:code> property changes when the button is clicked. Color types are animated using <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-coloranimation.xml">ColorAnimation</db:link> and numbers are animated using <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-numberanimation.xml">NumberAnimation</db:link>. The <db:code>on propertyName</db:code> syntax displayed below is helpful when targeting a single property.</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>Button.qml</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">...

color: buttonMouseArea.pressed ? Qt.darker(buttonColor, 1.5) : buttonColor
Behavior on color { ColorAnimation{ duration: 55 } }

scale: buttonMouseArea.pressed ? 1.1 : 1.0
Behavior on scale { NumberAnimation{ duration: 55 } }
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Additionally, we can enhance the appearances of our QML components by adding color effects such as gradients and opacity effects. Declaring a <db:link xlink:href="stylesheet-reference.xml#gradient">Gradient</db:link> object will override the <db:code>color</db:code> property. You may declare a color in the gradient using the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-gradientstop.xml">GradientStop</db:link> type. The gradient is positioned using a scale, between <db:code>0.0</db:code> and <db:code>1.0</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>MenuBar.qml</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">gradient: Gradient {
    GradientStop { position: 0.0; color: &quot;#8C8F8C&quot; }
    GradientStop { position: 0.17; color: &quot;#6A6D6A&quot; }
    GradientStop { position: 0.98; color: &quot;#3F3F3F&quot; }
    GradientStop { position: 1.0; color: &quot;#0e1B20&quot; }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>This gradient is used by the menu bar to display a gradient simulating depth. The first color starts at <db:code>0.0</db:code> and the last color is at <db:code>1.0</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="where-to-go-from-here">
<db:title>Where to Go from Here</db:title>
<db:para>We are finished building the user interface of a very simple text editor. Going forward, the user interface is complete, and we can implement the application logic using regular Qt and C++. QML works nicely as a prototyping tool, separating the application logic away from the UI design.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor4_texteditor.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="extending-qml-using-qt-c">
<db:title>Extending QML using Qt C++</db:title>
<db:para>Now that we have our text editor layout, we may now implement the text editor functionalities in C++. Using QML with C++ enables us to create our application logic using Qt. We can create a QML context in a C++ application using <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-cppintegration-topic.xml">Qt's Quick classes</db:link> and display the QML types using a <db:link xlink:href="qquickview.xml">QQuickView</db:link>. Alternatively, we can export our C++ code into an extension plugin, and make it accessible to QML as a new <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-identifiedmodules.xml">identified module</db:link>. When launching QML files with <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-qmlscene.xml">qmlscene</db:link>, we only need to ensure our module is found under one of the <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-syntax-imports.xml#qml-import-path">import paths</db:link> the QML engine searches for modules to import. For our application we shall the latter approach. This way, we can load the QML file directly with <db:code>qmlscene</db:code> instead of running an executable.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="exposing-c-classes-to-qml">
<db:title>Exposing C++ Classes to QML</db:title>
<db:para>We will be implementing file loading and saving using Qt and C++. C++ classes and functions can be used in QML by registering them. They also needs to be compiled as a Qt plugin and then exposed as a QML module.</db:para>
<db:para>For our application, we need to create the following items:</db:para>
<db:orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:code>Directory</db:code> class that will handle directory related operations</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:code>File</db:code> class which is a <db:link xlink:href="qobject.xml">QObject</db:link>, simulating the list of files in a directory</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>A plugin class that will register the classes to the QML context</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Qt project file that will compile the plugin</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>A <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">module definition qmldir file</db:link> that defines the identifier (import URI) and content (in this case, our plugin) to be made available by the QML module</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:orderedlist>
<db:note>
<db:para>Since Qt 5.1, <db:link xlink:href="qtquickdialogs-index.xml">Qt Quick Dialogs</db:link> module provides a file dialog component that you can use for choosing files from the local file system. For illustrative purposes, we write our own in this tutorial.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="building-a-qt-plugin">
<db:title>Building a Qt Plugin</db:title>
<db:para>To build a plugin, we need to set the following in a Qt project file. First, the necessary sources, headers, and Qt modules need to be added into our project file. All the C++ code and project files are in the <db:code>filedialog</db:code> directory.</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>filedialog.pro</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">TEMPLATE = lib
CONFIG += qt plugin
QT += qml

DESTDIR +=  ../imports/FileDialog
OBJECTS_DIR = tmp
MOC_DIR = tmp

TARGET = filedialogplugin

HEADERS += \
        directory.h \
        file.h \
        dialogPlugin.h

SOURCES += \
        directory.cpp \
        file.cpp \
        dialogPlugin.cpp
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>In particular, we link the project with the <db:code>qml</db:code> module and configure it as a <db:code>plugin</db:code>, using a <db:code>lib</db:code> template. We shall put the compiled plugin into the parent's <db:code>imports/FileDialog</db:code> directory.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="registering-a-class-into-qml">
<db:title>Registering a Class into QML</db:title>
<db:para>In <db:code>dialogPlugin.h</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">#include &lt;QtQml/QQmlExtensionPlugin&gt;

class DialogPlugin : public QQmlExtensionPlugin
{
    Q_OBJECT
    Q_PLUGIN_METADATA(IID &quot;org.qt-project.QmlExtensionPlugin.FileDialog&quot;)

public:
    // registerTypes is inherited from QQmlExtensionPlugin
    void registerTypes(const char *uri);
};

</db:programlisting>
<db:para>We need to export the plugin using the <db:link xlink:href="plugins-howto.xml">Q_PLUGIN_METADATA</db:link> macro. Note that in our <db:code>dialogPlugin.h</db:code> file, we have the <db:link xlink:href="qobject.xml#Q_OBJECT">Q_OBJECT</db:link> macro at the top of our class. As well, we need to run <db:code>qmake</db:code> on the project file to generate the necessary meta-object code.</db:para>
<db:para>Our plugin class, <db:code>DialogPlugin</db:code>, is a subclass of <db:link xlink:href="qqmlextensionplugin.xml">QQmlExtensionPlugin</db:link>. We need to implement the inherited function, <db:link xlink:href="qqmlextensionplugin.xml#registerTypes">registerTypes</db:link>().</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>DialogPlugin.cpp</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">#include &quot;dialogPlugin.h&quot;
#include &quot;directory.h&quot;
#include &quot;file.h&quot;
#include &lt;QtQml&gt;

void DialogPlugin::registerTypes(const char *uri)
{
    // Register the class Directory into QML as a &quot;Directory&quot; type version 1.0
    // @uri FileDialog
    qmlRegisterType&lt;Directory&gt;(uri, 1, 0, &quot;Directory&quot;);
    qmlRegisterType&lt;File&gt;(uri, 1, 0, &quot;File&quot;);
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The <db:code>registerTypes()</db:code> function registers our File and Directory classes into QML. This function needs the class name for its template, a major version number, a minor version number, and a name for our classes. A <db:code>// @uri &lt;module identifier&gt;</db:code> comment allows Qt Creator to be aware of the registered types when editing QML files that import this module.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="creating-qml-properties-in-a-c-class">
<db:title>Creating QML Properties in a C++ Class</db:title>
<db:para>We can create QML types and properties using C++ and <db:link xlink:href="metaobjects.xml">Qt's Meta-Object System</db:link>. We can implement properties using slots and signals, making Qt aware of these properties. These properties can then be used in QML.</db:para>
<db:para>For the text editor, we need to be able to load and save files. Typically, these features are contained in a file dialog. Fortunately, we can use <db:link xlink:href="qdir.xml">QDir</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qfile.xml">QFile</db:link>, and <db:link xlink:href="qtextstream.xml">QTextStream</db:link> to implement directory reading and input/output streams.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">class Directory : public QObject {
    Q_OBJECT

    Q_PROPERTY (int filesCount READ filesCount CONSTANT)
    Q_PROPERTY (QString filename READ filename WRITE setFilename NOTIFY filenameChanged)
    Q_PROPERTY (QString fileContent READ fileContent WRITE setFileContent NOTIFY fileContentChanged)
    Q_PROPERTY (QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt; files READ files CONSTANT)
    ...
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The <db:code>Directory</db:code> class uses Qt's Meta-Object System to register properties it needs to accomplish file handling. The <db:code>Directory</db:code> class is exported as a plugin and is useable in QML as the <db:code>Directory</db:code> type. Each of the listed properties using the <db:link xlink:href="qobject.xml#Q_PROPERTY">Q_PROPERTY</db:link>() macro is a QML property.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:link xlink:href="qobject.xml#Q_PROPERTY">Q_PROPERTY</db:link> declares a property as well as its read and write functions into Qt's Meta-Object System. For example, the <db:code>filename</db:code> property, of type <db:link xlink:href="qstring.xml">QString</db:link>, is readable using the <db:code>filename()</db:code> function and writable using the function <db:code>setFilename()</db:code>. Additionally, there is a signal associated to the filename property called <db:code>filenameChanged()</db:code>, which is emitted whenever the property changes. The read and write functions are declared as <db:code>public</db:code> in the header file.</db:para>
<db:para>Similarly, we have the other properties declared according to their uses. The <db:code>filesCount</db:code> property indicates the number of files in a directory. The filename property is set to the currently selected file's name and the loaded/saved file content is stored in <db:code>fileContent</db:code> property.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Q_PROPERTY(QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt; files READ files CONSTANT)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The <db:code>files</db:code> list property is a list of all the filtered files in a directory. The <db:code>Directory</db:code> class is implemented to filter out invalid text files; only files with a <db:code>.txt</db:code> extension are valid. Further, <db:link xlink:href="qlist.xml">QList</db:link>s can be used in QML files by declaring them as a <db:link xlink:href="qqmllistproperty.xml">QQmlListProperty</db:link> in C++. The templated object needs to inherit from a <db:link xlink:href="qobject.xml">QObject</db:link>, therefore, the <db:code>File</db:code> class must also inherit from <db:link xlink:href="qobject.xml">QObject</db:link>. In the <db:code>Directory</db:code> class, the list of <db:code>File</db:code> objects is stored in a <db:link xlink:href="qlist.xml">QList</db:link> called <db:code>m_fileList</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">class File : public QObject{

    Q_OBJECT
    Q_PROPERTY(QString name READ name WRITE setName NOTIFY nameChanged)

    ...
};
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The properties can then be used in QML as part of the <db:code>Directory</db:code> object's properties. Note that we do not have to create an identifier <db:code>id</db:code> property in our C++ code.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Directory {
    id: directory

    filesCount
    filename
    fileContent
    files

    files[0].name
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Because QML uses Javascript's syntax and structure, we can iterate through the list of files and retrieve its properties. To retrieve the first file's name property, we can call <db:code>files[0].name</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:para>Regular C++ functions are also accessible from QML. The file loading and saving functions are implemented in C++ and declared using the <db:link xlink:href="qobject.xml#Q_INVOKABLE">Q_INVOKABLE</db:link> macro. Alternatively, we can declare the functions as a <db:code>slot</db:code> and the functions will be accessible from QML.</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>directory.h</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Q_INVOKABLE void saveFile();
Q_INVOKABLE void loadFile();
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The <db:code>Directory</db:code> class also has to notify other objects whenever the directory contents change. This feature is performed using a <db:code>signal</db:code>. As previously mentioned, QML signals have a corresponding handler with their names prepended with <db:code>on</db:code>. The signal is called <db:code>directoryChanged</db:code> and it is emitted whenever there is a directory refresh. The refresh simply reloads the directory contents and updates the list of valid files in the directory. QML items can then be notified by attaching an action to the <db:code>onDirectoryChanged</db:code> signal handler.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:code>list</db:code> properties need to be explored further. This is because list properties use callbacks to access and modify the list contents. The list property is of type <db:code>QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt;</db:code>. Whenever the list is accessed, the accessor function needs to return a <db:code>QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt;</db:code>. The template type, <db:code>File</db:code>, needs to be a <db:code>QObject</db:code> derivative. Further, to create the <db:code>QQmlListProperty</db:code>, the list's accessor and modifiers need to be passed to the constructor as function pointers. The list, a <db:code>QList</db:code> in our case, also needs to be a list of <db:code>File</db:code> pointers.</db:para>
<db:para>The constructor of <db:link xlink:href="qqmllistproperty.xml">QQmlListProperty</db:link> is declared as follows:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">QQmlListProperty (QObject *object, void *data, AppendFunction append,
                  CountFunction count = 0, AtFunction at = 0, ClearFunction clear = 0);
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>It takes pointers to functions that will append the list, count the list, retrieve the item using an index, and empty the list. Only the <db:code>append</db:code> function is mandatory. Note that the function pointers must match the definition of <db:link xlink:href="qqmllistproperty.xml#AppendFunction-typedef">AppendFunction</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qqmllistproperty.xml#CountFunction-typedef">CountFunction</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qqmllistproperty.xml#AtFunction-typedef">AtFunction</db:link>, or <db:link xlink:href="qqmllistproperty.xml#ClearFunction-typedef">ClearFunction</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:code>Directory</db:code> class constructs a <db:link xlink:href="qqmllistproperty.xml">QQmlListProperty</db:link> instance like this:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt;(this, &amp;m_fileList, &amp;appendFiles, &amp;filesSize, &amp;fileAt, &amp;clearFilesPtr);
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Where the parameters are pointers to following functions:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">void appendFiles(QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt; *property, File *file);
File* fileAt(QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt; *property, int index);
int filesSize(QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt; *property);
void clearFilesPtr(QQmlListProperty&lt;File&gt; *property);
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>To simplify our file dialog, the <db:code>Directory</db:code> class filters out invalid text files, which are files that do not have a <db:code>.txt</db:code> extension. If a file name doesn't have the <db:code>.txt</db:code> extension, then it won't be seen in our file dialog. Also, the implementation makes sure that saved files have a <db:code>.txt</db:code> extension in the file name. <db:code>Directory</db:code> uses <db:link xlink:href="qtextstream.xml">QTextStream</db:link> to read the file and to output the file contents to a file.</db:para>
<db:para>With our <db:code>Directory</db:code> object, we can retrieve the files as a list, know how many text files is in the application directory, get the file's name and content as a string, and be notified whenever there are changes in the directory contents.</db:para>
<db:para>To build the plugin, run <db:code>qmake</db:code> on the <db:code>filedialog.pro</db:code> project file, then run <db:code>make</db:code> to build and transfer the plugin to the <db:code>plugins</db:code> directory.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="importing-a-plugin-in-qml">
<db:title>Importing a Plugin in QML</db:title>
<db:para>The <db:code>qmlscene</db:code> tool imports files that are in the same directory as the application. We can also create a <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file containing the locations of content we wish to import. In this case, there is only the plugin, but other resources (QML types, JavaScript files) can be defined in a <db:code>qmldir</db:code> as well.</db:para>
<db:para>Contents of the <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">module FileDialog
plugin filedialogplugin
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The module we just created is called <db:code>FileDialog</db:code>, and it makes available a plugin called <db:code>filedialogplugin</db:code> that matches the <db:code>TARGET</db:code> field in the project file. Because we did not specify a path for the plugin, the QML engine expects to find it in the same directory as the <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file.</db:para>
<db:para>The QML types that are registered by our plugin can now be imported in QML:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">import FileDialog 1.0

Directory {
    id: directory
}
...
</db:programlisting>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="integrating-a-file-dialog-into-the-file-menu">
<db:title>Integrating a File Dialog into the File Menu</db:title>
<db:para>Our <db:code>FileMenu</db:code> needs to display the <db:code>FileDialog</db:code> object, containing a list of the text files in a directory thus allowing the user to select the file by clicking on the list. We also need to assign the save, load, and new buttons to their respective actions. The FileMenu contains an editable text input to allow the user to type a file name using the keyboard.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:code>Directory</db:code> object is used in the <db:code>FileMenu.qml</db:code> file and it notifies the <db:code>FileDialog</db:code> object that the directory refreshed its contents. This notification is performed in the signal handler, <db:code>onDirectoryChanged</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>FileMenu.qml</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Directory {
    id: directory
    filename: textInput.text
    onDirectoryChanged: fileDialog.notifyRefresh()
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Keeping with the simplicity of our application, the file dialog will always be visible and will not display invalid text files, which do not have a <db:code>.txt</db:code> extension to their filenames.</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>FileDialog.qml</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">signal notifyRefresh()
onNotifyRefresh: dirView.model = directory.files
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The <db:code>FileDialog</db:code> object will display the contents of a directory by reading its list property called <db:code>files</db:code>. The files are used as the model of a <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-gridview.xml">GridView</db:link> object, which displays data items in a grid according to a delegate. The delegate handles the appearance of the model and our file dialog will simply create a grid with text centered in the middle. Clicking on the file name will result in the appearance of a rectangle to highlight the file name. The <db:code>FileDialog</db:code> is notified whenever the <db:code>notifyRefresh</db:code> signal is emitted, reloading the files in the directory.</db:para>
<db:para>In <db:code>FileMenu.qml</db:code>:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">Button {
    id: newButton
    label: &quot;New&quot;
    onButtonClick: {
        textArea.textContent = &quot;&quot;
    }
}
Button {
    id: loadButton
    label: &quot;Load&quot;
    onButtonClick: {
        directory.filename = textInput.text
        directory.loadFile()
        textArea.textContent = directory.fileContent
    }
}
Button {
    id: saveButton
    label: &quot;Save&quot;
    onButtonClick: {
        directory.fileContent = textArea.textContent
        directory.filename = textInput.text
        directory.saveFile()
    }
}
Button {
    id: exitButton
    label: &quot;Exit&quot;
    onButtonClick: {
        Qt.quit()
    }
}
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Our <db:code>FileMenu</db:code> can now connect to their respective actions. The <db:code>saveButton</db:code> will transfer the text from the <db:code>TextEdit</db:code> onto the directory's <db:code>fileContent</db:code> property, then copy its file name from the editable text input. Finally, the button calls the <db:code>saveFile()</db:code> function, saving the file. The <db:code>loadButton</db:code> has a similar execution. Also, the <db:code>New</db:code> action will empty the contents of the <db:code>TextEdit</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:para>Further, the <db:code>EditMenu</db:code> buttons are connected to the <db:code>TextEdit</db:code> functions to copy, paste, and select all the text in the text editor.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor5_filemenu.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="final-text-editor-application">
<db:title>Final Text Editor Application</db:title>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qml-texteditor5_newfile.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>The application can function as a simple text editor, able to accept text and save it into a file. It can also load a file and perform text manipulation.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="running-the-text-editor">
<db:title>Running the Text Editor</db:title>
<db:para>We need to build the file dialog C++ plugin before the text editor can run. To build it, enter the <db:code>filedialog</db:code> directory, then run <db:code>qmake</db:code> and compile using <db:code>make</db:code> or <db:code>nmake</db:code>, depending on your platform.</db:para>
<db:para>Run the text editor with <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-qmlscene.xml">qmlscene</db:link>, passing the imports directory as a parameter so that the QML engine knows where to look for the module that imports our file dialog plugin:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">qmlscene -I ./imports texteditor.qml
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The complete source code is in <db:code>examples/quick/tutorials/gettingStartedQml</db:code> directory.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
