<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Inter-Process Communication in Qt</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.15.0 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Inter-Process communication in Qt applications.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>Qt provides several ways to implement Inter-Process Communication (IPC) in Qt applications.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="tcp-ip">
<db:title>TCP/IP</db:title>
<db:para>The cross-platform <db:link xlink:href="qtnetwork-index.xml">Qt Network</db:link> module provides classes that make network programming portable and easy. It offers high-level classes (e.g. <db:link xlink:href="qnetworkaccessmanager.xml">QNetworkAccessManager</db:link>) that communicate using specific application-level protocols, and lower-level classes (e.g., <db:link xlink:href="qtcpsocket.xml">QTcpSocket</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qtcpserver.xml">QTcpServer</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qsslsocket.xml">QSslSocket</db:link>) for implementing protocols.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="local-server-socket">
<db:title>Local Server/Socket</db:title>
<db:para>The cross-platform <db:link xlink:href="qtnetwork-index.xml">Qt Network</db:link> module provides classes that make local network programming portable and easy. It offers the <db:link xlink:href="qlocalserver.xml">QLocalServer</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="qlocalsocket.xml">QLocalSocket</db:link> classes that allow for network-like communication in a local setup. Their TCP counterparts can be used as drop-in replacement to make the communication work across networks.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="shared-memory">
<db:title>Shared Memory</db:title>
<db:para>The cross-platform shared memory class, <db:link xlink:href="qsharedmemory.xml">QSharedMemory</db:link>, provides access to the operating system's shared memory implementation. It allows safe access to shared memory segments by multiple threads and processes. Additionally, <db:link xlink:href="qsystemsemaphore.xml">QSystemSemaphore</db:link> can be used to control access to resources shared by the system, as well as to communicate between processes.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="d-bus-protocol">
<db:title>D-Bus protocol</db:title>
<db:para>The <db:link xlink:href="qtdbus-index.xml">Qt D-Bus</db:link> module is a Unix-only library you can use to implement IPC using the D-Bus protocol. It extends Qt's <db:link xlink:href="signalsandslots.xml">Signals and Slots</db:link> mechanism to the IPC level, allowing a signal emitted by one process to be connected to a slot in another process. The <db:link xlink:href="qtdbus-index.xml">Qt D-Bus</db:link> documentation has detailed information on how to use the <db:link xlink:href="qtdbus-index.xml">Qt D-Bus</db:link> module.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="qprocess-class">
<db:title>QProcess Class</db:title>
<db:para>The cross-platform class <db:link xlink:href="qprocess.xml">QProcess</db:link> can be used to start external programs as child processes, and to communicate with them. It provides an API for monitoring and controlling the state of the child process. <db:link xlink:href="qprocess.xml">QProcess</db:link> gives access to the input/output channels of child process by inheriting from <db:link xlink:href="qiodevice.xml">QIODevice</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="session-management">
<db:title>Session Management</db:title>
<db:para>On Linux/X11, Windows and macOS, Qt provides support for session management. Sessions allow events to be propagated to processes, for example, to notify when a shutdown occurs. The process and applications can then perform any necessary operations such as save open documents.</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="session.xml">Session Management</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
</db:article>
