<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Reusing translations</db:title>
<db:productname>QtLinguist</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.6.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Linguist Manual</db:titleabbrev>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="linguist-viewing-strings-in-context.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="prev" xlink:title="Viewing strings in context"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="linguist-validating-translations.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="next" xlink:title="Validating translations"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt Linguist Manual.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>If the translated text is similar to the source text, select <db:guilabel>Translation</db:guilabel> &gt; <db:guilabel>Copy from source text</db:guilabel> (or press <db:emphasis role="bold">Ctrl+B</db:emphasis>) to copy the source text into the translation area.</db:para>
<db:para><db:emphasis>Phrase books</db:emphasis> provide a common set of translations to help ensure consistency. A phrase book is a set of source phrases, target (translated) phrases, and optional definitions. Typically, one phrase book is created per language and family of applications. Phrase books avoid duplication of effort since they contain translations for a family of applications.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:guilabel>Phrases and guesses</db:guilabel> view displays the current string and its phrase book translations. If the current string is the same as or similar to a translated string, the view also lists the string and its translation.</db:para>
<db:para>To copy a translation from the <db:guilabel>Phrases and guesses</db:guilabel> view to the translation area, double-click it or select it and press <db:emphasis role="bold">Enter</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="batch-translation">
<db:title>Batch translation</db:title>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/linguist-batchtranslation.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>Use the batch translation feature to automatically translate source texts that are also in a phrase book. To configure which phrase books to use in what order during the batch translation process, select <db:guilabel>Edit</db:guilabel> &gt; <db:guilabel>Batch Translation</db:guilabel>. You can include only entries with no current translation and mark batch translated entries as <db:guilabel>Accepted</db:guilabel>.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="creating-and-editing-phrase-books">
<db:title>Creating and editing phrase books</db:title>
<db:para>Phrase book files are human-readable XML files containing standard phrases and their translations. <db:emphasis>Qt Linguist</db:emphasis> creates and update the files. You can use them for any number of projects and applications.</db:para>
<db:para>To create a new phrase book, select <db:guilabel>Phrases</db:guilabel> &gt; <db:guilabel>New Phrase Book</db:guilabel>.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/linguist-phrasebookdialog.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>To open a phrase book, select <db:guilabel>Phrases</db:guilabel> &gt; <db:guilabel>Open Phrase Book</db:guilabel>, and then select the Qt phrase book file (.qph) to open.</db:para>
<db:para>To view and change open phrase books, select <db:guilabel>Phrases</db:guilabel> &gt; <db:guilabel>Edit Phrase Book</db:guilabel>.</db:para>
<db:para>To add a new phrase, select <db:guilabel>New Entry</db:guilabel> (or press <db:emphasis role="bold">Alt+N</db:emphasis>) and type in a new source phrase, the translation, and an optional definition. This is useful to distinguish different translations of the same source phrase.</db:para>
<db:para>To add the translation you are working on to the current phrase book, select <db:guilabel>Phrases</db:guilabel> &gt; <db:guilabel>Add to Phrase Book</db:guilabel> or press <db:emphasis role="bold">Ctrl+T</db:emphasis>. If multiple phrase books are loaded, you have to select one.</db:para>
<db:para>If you detect an error in a phrase book entry in the <db:guilabel>Phrases and guesses</db:guilabel> view, you can edit by right clicking it and selecting <db:guilabel>Edit</db:guilabel>. After fixing the error press <db:emphasis role="bold">Enter</db:emphasis> to leave the editing mode.</db:para>
<db:para>To delete a phrase, select it in the <db:guilabel>Source phrase</db:guilabel> list, and then select <db:guilabel>Remove Entry</db:guilabel>.</db:para>
<db:para>To print an open phrase book, select <db:guilabel>Phrases</db:guilabel> &gt; <db:guilabel>Print Phrase Book</db:guilabel>.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
