<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Validating translations</db:title>
<db:productname>QtLinguist</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.5.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Linguist Manual</db:titleabbrev>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="linguist-reusing-translations.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="prev" xlink:title="Reusing translations"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="linguist-translating-multiple-languages.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="next" xlink:title="Translating multiple languages simultaneously"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt Linguist Manual.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-02-14</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-02-14</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para><db:emphasis>Qt Linguist</db:emphasis> provides the following validation tests for translations:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis>Accelerator validation</db:emphasis> detects translated phrases that do not have an ampersand when the source phrase does and vice versa.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis>Punctuation validation</db:emphasis> detects differences in the terminating punctuation between source and translated phrases when this may be significant. For example, warns if the source phrase ends with an ellipsis, exclamation mark or question mark, and the translated phrase does not, and vice versa.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis>Phrases validation</db:emphasis> detects source phrases that are also in the phrase book but whose translation differs from that in the phrase book.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:emphasis>Place marker validation</db:emphasis> detects whether the same variables (like <db:code>%1</db:code>, <db:code>%2</db:code>) appear both in the source text and in the translation.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>To switch validation tests on or off, select <db:guilabel>Validation</db:guilabel> or use the toolbar buttons.</db:para>
<db:para>Not accepted strings that fail validation tests are marked with the <db:guilabel>Validation Failures</db:guilabel> icon in the <db:guilabel>Strings</db:guilabel> view. Accepted strings are marked with <db:guilabel>Accepted/Warnings</db:guilabel>.</db:para>
<db:para>If you switch validation off and then switch it on later, <db:emphasis>Qt Linguist</db:emphasis> rechecks all phrases and marks any that fail validation.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:guilabel>Warnings</db:guilabel> view lists the strings that fail the active validation tests. The first warning is also shown in the status bar at the bottom of the main window.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Only results of <db:emphasis>active</db:emphasis> validation tests are reported.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:article>
