<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Creating translation files</db:title>
<db:productname>QtLinguist</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.5.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Linguist Manual</db:titleabbrev>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="linguist-manager.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="prev" xlink:title="Release managers"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:extendedlink xlink:type="extended"><db:link xlink:to="linguist-lupdate.xml" xlink:type="arc" xlink:arcrole="next" xlink:title="Using lupdate"/></db:extendedlink>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt Linguist Manual.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-02-14</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-02-14</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>Most of the text to translate in an application consists of either single words or short phrases. These typically appear as window titles, menu items, tooltips, and labels to buttons, check boxes, and radio buttons.</db:para>
<db:para>Developers mark the phrases as translatable in the QML and C++ source code. The Qt tools provide context information for each of the phrases to help the translator understand their meaning. The developer can add comments to the phrases.</db:para>
<db:para>Translation files consist of all the user-visible text and <db:emphasis role="bold">Ctrl</db:emphasis> key shortcuts in an application and translations of that text.</db:para>
<db:para>To create translation files:</db:para>
<db:orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Run <db:code>lupdate</db:code> to generate the first set of translation source (TS) files with all the user-visible text but no translations.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Give the TS files to translators who add translations using <db:emphasis>Qt Linguist</db:emphasis>. <db:emphasis>Qt Linguist</db:emphasis> indicates changed and deleted source text.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Run <db:code>lupdate</db:code> to incorporate any new text added to the application. <db:code>lupdate</db:code> synchronizes the user-visible text from the application with the translations. It does not destroy any data.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Run <db:code>lrelease</db:code> to read the TS files and produce the QM files used by the application at runtime.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:orderedlist>
<db:para>For <db:code>lupdate</db:code> to work successfully, it must know which translation files to produce. Specify the files in the application's Qt project file.</db:para>
<db:para>When building with CMake, you use <db:link xlink:href="cmake-commands-qtlinguisttools.xml">CMake commands</db:link> to add targets that create or update TS files and transform them into QM files. The translation files are generated when you build the targets.</db:para>
</db:article>
