<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt for Linux/X11 - Specific Issues</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.15.0 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>A description of issues with Qt that are specific to Linux/X11.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>This page contains information about the X11 platforms Qt is currently known to run on, with links to platform-specific notes.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="linux">
<db:title>Linux</db:title>
<db:para>There are no known problems with using Qt on production versions of Linux/x86, Linux/ppc, Linux/amd64 and Linux/ia64 (including Altix(R)).</db:para>
<db:para>For information about the specific compilers supported, visit the <db:link xlink:href="supported-platforms.xml#reference-configurations">supported platforms</db:link> page.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="installation-problems">
<db:title>Installation problems</db:title>
<db:para>Installing the source (<db:emphasis>.tgz</db:emphasis>) will likely conflict with the Qt version from your Linux distribution. This can result in link errors, such as:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">undefined reference to '_vt.11QPushButton'
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>This is solved by removing the older version of the library.</db:para>
<db:para>If you have problems installing open source versions of Qt provided by your Linux distribution, for example, from RPM or APT repositories, please consult the maintainers of the distribution.</db:para>
<db:para>Some RPM versions have problems installing some of the Qt RPM archives where installation stops with an error message warning about a <db:emphasis role="bold">Failed Dependency</db:emphasis>. Use the --nodeps option of rpm as workaround this problem.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="intel-c-compiler-for-linux">
<db:title>Intel C++ Compiler for Linux</db:title>
<db:para>Qt can be compiled with the Intel C++ compile for Linux, though, this configuration is not tested on a regular basis.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="known-issues-with-intel-c-compiler-for-linux">
<db:title>Known Issues with Intel C++ Compiler for Linux</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Precompiled header support does not work in version 10.0.025 and older. For these compilers, you should configure Qt with -no-pch. Precompiled header support works properly in version 10.0.026 and later.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Version 10.0.026 for Intel 64 is known to miscompile qmake when building in release mode. For now, configure Qt with -debug. Version 10.1.008 and later can compile qmake in release mode.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Versions 10.1.008 to 10.1.015 for both IA-32 and Intel 64 are known crash with &quot;(0): internal error: 0_47021&quot; when compiling <db:link xlink:href="qtxmlpatterns-index.xml">Qt XML Patterns</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="qtdesigner-index.xml">Qt Designer</db:link> in release mode. Version 10.1.017 compiles these modules correctly in release mode.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="known-issues-with-gcc-compilers">
<db:title>Known Issues with GCC Compilers</db:title>
<db:para>Building Qt with certain versions of GCC has the following known issues:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>GCC 5.2.1: Nested structs do not get their constructors called under some circumstances:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=67550">Related bug</db:link> in GCC's bug tracker</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://codereview.qt-project.org/161071">A possible workaround</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
</db:section>
</db:article>
