<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Porting Guide</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.12.12 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Provides guidance to migrate your Qt 4 application to Qt 5.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>Qt 5 is a result of the conscious effort to make this C++ framework more efficient and easy to use. This release replaces quite a few legacy APIs with more meaningful ones, such as the newer version of Qt Quick.</db:para>
<db:para>We try to maintain binary and source compatibility for all the public APIs in each release, but some changes were inevitable in an effort to make Qt a better framework. In this topic, we try to summarize those changes and provide guidance to handle them.</db:para>
<db:para>The following list summarizes the changes in Qt 5:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Modularized codebase - This means only Qt essentials and the add-on modules you're interested in are needed to develop an application. To know what makes the essentials and add-on modules, refer to the <db:link xlink:href="qtmodules.xml">modules</db:link> page.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Platform-specific code - Symbian and Meego-specific code is removed from the codebase.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Platform defines - All platform-specific code must be wrapped using the preprocessor macro, Q_OS_* instead of Q_WS_*.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Widgets - These are now part of a separate module, <db:link xlink:href="qtwidgets-index.xml">Qt Widgets</db:link>. They were part of <db:link xlink:href="qtgui-index.xml">Qt GUI</db:link> earlier.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Qt Quick - The older Qt Quick version (1.0) is now part of a separate <db:link xlink:href="http://doc.qt.io/qt-4.8/qtdeclarative-module.html">Qt Declarative</db:link> add-on module for compatibility purposes. We recommend using the new Qt Quick (2.0) from now on to avoid binary breaks in the future.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Qt3Support - This module is removed in Qt 5, so you must move away from this module before porting your codebase to Qt 5.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Qt WebKit - This module has been replaced with <db:link xlink:href="qtwebengine-index.xml">Qt WebEngine</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Multimedia - In Qt 5, multimedia support is provided by the <db:link xlink:href="qtmultimedia-index.xml">Qt Multimedia</db:link> module. Phonon framework is no longer part of Qt, but it continues to be maintained by the Phonon developers and has support for Qt 5. See <db:link xlink:href="http://phonon.kde.org">http://phonon.kde.org</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:section xml:id="related-topics">
<db:title>Related Topics</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="sourcebreaks.xml">C++ API Changes</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="portingcppapp.xml">Porting C++ Applications to Qt 5</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qtquick-porting-qt5.xml">Porting QML Applications to Qt 5</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="portingqmlapp.xml">Porting QML Applications to Qt 5 Example</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
</db:article>
