<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>qt_add_qml_module</db:title>
<db:productname>QtQml</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.7.2 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt QML Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Defines a QML module.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:anchor xml:id="qt6-add-qml-module"/>
<db:para>This command was introduced in Qt 6.2.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="synopsis">
<db:title>Synopsis</db:title>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">qt_add_qml_module(
    target
    URI uri
    [VERSION version]
    [PAST_MAJOR_VERSIONS ...]
    [STATIC | SHARED]
    [PLUGIN_TARGET plugin_target]
    [OUTPUT_DIRECTORY output_dir]
    [RESOURCE_PREFIX resource_prefix]
    [CLASS_NAME class_name]
    [TYPEINFO typeinfo]
    [IMPORTS ...]
    [OPTIONAL_IMPORTS ...]
    [DEFAULT_IMPORTS ...]
    [DEPENDENCIES ...]
    [IMPORT_PATH ...]
    [SOURCES ...]
    [QML_FILES ...]
    [RESOURCES ...]
    [OUTPUT_TARGETS out_targets_var]
    [DESIGNER_SUPPORTED]
    [FOLLOW_FOREIGN_VERSIONING]
    [NAMESPACE namespace]
    [NO_PLUGIN]
    [NO_PLUGIN_OPTIONAL]
    [NO_CREATE_PLUGIN_TARGET]
    [NO_GENERATE_PLUGIN_SOURCE]
    [NO_GENERATE_QMLTYPES]
    [NO_GENERATE_QMLDIR]
    [NO_LINT]
    [NO_CACHEGEN]
    [NO_RESOURCE_TARGET_PATH]
    [NO_IMPORT_SCAN]
    [ENABLE_TYPE_COMPILER]
    [TYPE_COMPILER_NAMESPACE namespace]
    [QMLTC_EXPORT_DIRECTIVE export_macro]
    [QMLTC_EXPORT_FILE_NAME header_defining_export_macro]

)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>If <db:link xlink:href="cmake-qt5-and-qt6-compatibility.xml#versionless-commands">versionless commands</db:link> are disabled, use <db:code>qt6_add_qml_module()</db:code> instead. It supports the same set of arguments as this command.</db:para>
<db:para>See <db:link xlink:href="cmake-build-qml-application.xml">Building a QML application</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="cmake-build-reusable-qml-module.xml">Building a reusable QML module</db:link> for examples that define QML modules.</db:para>
<db:para>See <db:link xlink:href="cmake-variable-qt-qml-generate-qmlls-ini.xml">QT_QML_GENERATE_QMLLS_INI</db:link> for configuring your project such that information about QML modules is exposed to the <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-tools-and-utilities.xml#qml-language-server">QML Language Server</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="description">
<db:title>Description</db:title>
<db:para>This command defines a QML module that can consist of C++ sources, <db:code>.qml</db:code> files, or both. It ensures that essential module details are provided and that they are consistent. It also sets up and coordinates things like cached compilation of <db:code>.qml</db:code> sources, resource embedding, linting checks, and auto-generation of some key module files.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="target-structure">
<db:title>Target Structure</db:title>
<db:para>A QML module can be structured in a few different ways. The following scenarios are the typical arrangements:</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="separate-backing-and-plugin-targets">
<db:title>Separate backing and plugin targets</db:title>
<db:para>This is the recommended arrangement for most QML modules. All of the module's functionality is implemented in the <db:emphasis>backing</db:emphasis> target, which is given as the first command argument. C++ sources, <db:code>.qml</db:code> files, and resources should all be added to the backing target. The backing target is a library that should be installed in the same location as any other library defined by the project.</db:para>
<db:para>The source directory structure under which the backing target is created should match the target path of the QML module (the target path is the module's URI with dots replaced by forward slashes). If the source directory structure doesn't match the target path, <db:code>qt_add_qml_module()</db:code> will issue a warning.</db:para>
<db:para>The following example shows a suitable source directory structure for a QML module with a URI of <db:code>MyThings.Panels</db:code>. The call to <db:code>qt_add_qml_module()</db:code> would be in the <db:code>CMakeLists.txt</db:code> file shown.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">src
 +-- MyThings
      +-- Panels
           +-- CMakeLists.txt
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>A separate <db:emphasis>plugin</db:emphasis> target is associated with the QML module. It is used at runtime to load the module dynamically when the application doesn't already link to the backing target. The plugin target will also be a library and is normally installed to the same directory as the module's <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file.</db:para>
<db:para>The plugin target should ideally contain nothing more than a trivial implementation of the plugin class. This allows the plugin to be designated as optional in the <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file. Other targets can then link directly to the backing target and the plugin will not be needed at runtime, which can improve load-time performance. By default, a C++ source file that defines a minimal plugin class will be automatically generated and added to the plugin target. For cases where the QML module needs a custom plugin class implementation, the <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#no-generate-plugin-source">NO_GENERATE_PLUGIN_SOURCE</db:link> and usually the <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#no-plugin-optional">NO_PLUGIN_OPTIONAL</db:link> options will be needed.</db:para>
<db:para>The <db:code>STATIC</db:code> QML modules also generate the static QML plugins if <db:code>NO_PLUGIN</db:code> is not specified. Targets that import such <db:code>STATIC</db:code> QML modules also need to explicitly link to corresponding QML plugins.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>When using static linking, it might be necessary to use <db:link xlink:href="qqmlengineextensionplugin.xml#Q_IMPORT_QML_PLUGIN">Q_IMPORT_QML_PLUGIN</db:link> to ensure that the QML plugin is correctly linked.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="plugin-target-with-no-backing-target">
<db:title>Plugin target with no backing target</db:title>
<db:para>A QML module can be defined with the plugin target serving as its own backing target. In this case, the module must be loaded dynamically at runtime and cannot be linked to directly by other targets. To create this arrangement, the <db:code>PLUGIN_TARGET</db:code> keyword must be used, with the <db:code>target</db:code> repeated as the plugin target name. For example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">qt_add_qml_module(someTarget
    PLUGIN_TARGET someTarget
    ...
)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>While this arrangement may seem marginally simpler to deploy, a separate backing target should be preferred where possible due to the potentially better load-time performance.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="executable-as-a-qml-module">
<db:title>Executable as a QML module</db:title>
<db:para>An executable target can act as a backing target for a QML module. In this case, there will be no plugin library, since the QML module will always be loaded directly as part of the application. The <db:code>qt_add_qml_module()</db:code> command will detect when an executable is used as the backing target and will automatically disable the creation of a separate plugin. Do not use any of the options with <db:code>PLUGIN</db:code> in their name when using this arrangement.</db:para>
<db:para>When an executable is used as the backing target, the source directory structure is not expected to match the QML module's target path. See <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#qmlcachegen-auto">Caching compiled QML sources</db:link> for additional target path differences for compiled-in resources.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="qmldir-autogeneration"/>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="auto-generating-qmldir-and-typeinfo-files">
<db:title>Auto-generating <db:code>qmldir</db:code> and typeinfo files</db:title>
<db:para>By default, a <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file and a typeinfo file will be auto-generated for the QML module being defined. The contents of those files are determined by the various arguments given to this command, as well as the sources and <db:code>.qml</db:code> files added to the backing target. The <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#output-directory">OUTPUT_DIRECTORY</db:link> argument determines where the <db:code>qmldir</db:code> and typeinfo files will be written to. If the QML module has a plugin, that plugin will also be created in the same directory as the <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file.</db:para>
<db:para>If using a statically built Qt, the backing target's <db:code>.qml</db:code> files will be scanned during the CMake configure run to determine the imports used by the module and to set up linking relationships (the <db:code>NO_IMPORT_SCAN</db:code> keyword can be given to disable this). When a <db:code>.qml</db:code> file is added to or removed from the module, CMake will normally re-run automatically and the relevant files will be re-scanned, since a <db:code>CMakeLists.txt</db:code> file will have been modified. During the course of development, an existing <db:code>.qml</db:code> file may add or remove an import or a type. On its own, this would not cause CMake to re-run automatically, so you should explicitly re-run CMake to force the <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file to be regenerated and any linking relationships to be updated.</db:para>
<db:para>The backing target's C++ sources are scanned at build time to generate a typeinfo file and a C++ file to register the associated types. The generated C++ file is automatically added to the backing target as a source. This requires <db:code>AUTOMOC</db:code> to be enabled on the target. The project is responsible for ensuring this, usually by setting the <db:code>CMAKE_AUTOMOC</db:code> variable to <db:code>TRUE</db:code> before calling <db:code>qt_add_qml_module()</db:code>, or by passing in an existing target with the <db:code>AUTOMOC</db:code> target property already set to <db:code>TRUE</db:code>. It isn't an error to have <db:code>AUTOMOC</db:code> disabled on the target, but the project is then responsible for handling the consequences. This may include having to manually generate the typeinfo file instead of allowing it to be auto-generated with missing details, and adding C++ code to register the types.</db:para>
<db:para>Projects should prefer to use the auto-generated typeinfo and <db:code>qmldir</db:code> files where possible. They are easier to maintain and they don't suffer from the same susceptibility to errors that hand-written files do. Nevertheless, for situations where the project needs to provide these files itself, the auto-generation can be disabled. The <db:code>NO_GENERATE_QMLDIR</db:code> option disables the <db:code>qmldir</db:code> auto-generation and the <db:code>NO_GENERATE_QMLTYPES</db:code> option disables the typeinfo and C++ type registration auto-generation. If the auto-generated typeinfo file is acceptable, but the project wants to use a different name for that file, it can override the default name with the <db:code>TYPEINFO</db:code> option (but this should not typically be needed).</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="qmlcachegen-auto"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="caching-compiled-qml-sources">
<db:title>Caching compiled QML sources</db:title>
<db:para>All <db:code>.qml</db:code>, <db:code>.js</db:code>, and <db:code>.mjs</db:code> files added to the module via the <db:code>QML_FILES</db:code> argument will be compiled to bytecode and cached directly in the backing target. This improves load-time performance of the module. The original uncompiled files are also stored in the backing target's resources, as these may still be needed in certain situations by the QML engine.</db:para>
<db:para>The resource path of each file is determined by its path relative to the current source directory (<db:code>CMAKE_CURRENT_SOURCE_DIR</db:code>). This resource path is appended to a prefix formed by concatenating the <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#resource-prefix">RESOURCE_PREFIX</db:link> and the target path (but see <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#no-resource-target-path">NO_RESOURCE_TARGET_PATH</db:link> for an exception to this).</db:para>
<db:para>If <db:link xlink:href="qt-cmake-policy-qtp0001.xml">QTP0001</db:link> policy is set to <db:code>NEW</db:code>, the <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#resource-prefix">RESOURCE_PREFIX</db:link> defaults to <db:code>/qt/qml/</db:code> which is the default import path of the QML engine. This ensures that modules are put into the <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-syntax-imports.xml#qml-import-path">QML Import Path</db:link> and can be found without further setup.</db:para>
<db:para>Ordinarily, the project should aim to place <db:code>.qml</db:code> files in the same relative location as they would have in the resources. If the <db:code>.qml</db:code> file is in a different relative directory to its desired resource path, its location in the resources needs to be explicitly specified. This is done by setting the <db:code>QT_RESOURCE_ALIAS</db:code> source file property, which must be set before the <db:code>.qml</db:code> file is added. For example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">set_source_files_properties(path/to/somewhere/MyFrame.qml PROPERTIES
    QT_RESOURCE_ALIAS MyFrame.qml
)

qt_add_qml_module(someTarget
    URI MyCo.Frames
    RESOURCE_PREFIX /my.company.com/imports
    QML_FILES
        path/to/somewhere/MyFrame.qml
        AnotherFrame.qml
)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>In the above example, the target path will be <db:code>MyCo/Frames</db:code>. After taking into account the source file properties, the two <db:code>.qml</db:code> files will be found at the following resource paths:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:code>/my.company.com/imports/MyCo/Frames/MyFrame.qml</db:code></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:code>/my.company.com/imports/MyCo/Frames/AnotherFrame.qml</db:code></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>In the rare case that you want to override the automatic selection of the qmlcachegen program to be used, you may set the <db:code>QT_QMLCACHEGEN_EXECUTABLE</db:code> target property on the module target. For example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">set_target_properties(someTarget PROPERTIES
    QT_QMLCACHEGEN_EXECUTABLE qmlcachegen
)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>This explicitly selects qmlcachegen as the program to be used, even if better alternatives are available.</db:para>
<db:para>Furthermore, you can pass extra arguments to qmlcachegen, by setting the <db:code>QT_QMLCACHEGEN_ARGUMENTS</db:code> option. In particular, the <db:code>--only-bytecode</db:code> option will turn off compilation of QML script code to C++. For example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">set_target_properties(someTarget PROPERTIES
    QT_QMLCACHEGEN_ARGUMENTS &quot;--only-bytecode&quot;
)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Another important argument is <db:code>--direct-calls</db:code>. You can use it to enable the direct mode of <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-qtquick-compiler-tech.xml#the-qml-script-compiler">The QML script compiler</db:link> in case the Qt Quick Compiler Extensions are installed. If the extensions are not installed, the argument is ignored. There is a shorthand called <db:code>QT_QMLCACHEGEN_DIRECT_CALLS</db:code> for it.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">set_target_properties(someTarget PROPERTIES
    QT_QMLCACHEGEN_DIRECT_CALLS ON
)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>Finally, the <db:code>--verbose</db:code> argument can be used to see diagnostic output from qmlcachegen:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">set_target_properties(someTarget PROPERTIES
    QT_QMLCACHEGEN_ARGUMENTS &quot;--verbose&quot;
)
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>With this flag set, qmlcachegen will output warnings for each function it cannot compile to C++. Some of these warnings will point to problems in your QML code and some will tell you that certain features of the QML language are not implemented in the C++ code generator. In both cases, qmlcachegen will still generate byte code for such functions. If you want to see only the problems in your QML code, you should use qmllint and the targets generated for it instead.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="qmllint-auto"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="linting-qml-sources">
<db:title>Linting QML sources</db:title>
<db:para>A separate linting target will be automatically created if any <db:code>.qml</db:code> files are added to the module via the <db:code>QML_FILES</db:code> keyword, or by a later call to <db:link xlink:href="qt-target-qml-sources.xml#qt6-target-qml-sources">qt_target_qml_sources()</db:link>. The name of the linting target will be the <db:code>target</db:code> followed by <db:code>_qmllint</db:code>. An <db:code>all_qmllint</db:code> target which depends on all the individual <db:code>*_qmllint</db:code> targets is also provided as a convenience.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="qml-naming-js-files"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="naming-conventions-for-op-op-js-files">
<db:title>Naming conventions for <db:code>.js</db:code> files</db:title>
<db:para>JavaScript file names that are intended to be addressed as components should start with an uppercase letter.</db:para>
<db:para>Alternatively, you may use lowercase file names and set the source file property <db:link xlink:href="cmake-source-file-property-qt-qml-source-typename.xml">QT_QML_SOURCE_TYPENAME</db:link> to the desired type name.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="qml-cmake-singletons"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="singletons">
<db:title>Singletons</db:title>
<db:para>If a QML module has <db:code>.qml</db:code> files which provide singleton types, these files need to have their <db:code>QT_QML_SINGLETON_TYPE</db:code> source property set to <db:code>TRUE</db:code>, to ensure that the <db:code>singleton</db:code> command is written into the <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file. This must be done in addition to the QML file containing the <db:code>pragma Singleton</db:code> statement. The source property must be set before creating the module the singleton belongs to.</db:para>
<db:para>See <db:link xlink:href="qt-target-qml-sources.xml#qt-target-qml-sources-example">qt_target_qml_sources()</db:link> for an example on how to set the <db:code>QT_QML_SINGLETON_TYPE</db:code> property.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="qmltc-cmake"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="compiling-qml-to-c-with-qml-type-compiler">
<db:title>Compiling QML to C++ with QML type compiler</db:title>
<db:note>
<db:para>The <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-qml-type-compiler.xml">QML type compiler</db:link> <db:code>qmltc</db:code> does not guarantee that the generated C++ stays API-, source- or binary-compatible between past or future versions, even patch versions. Furthermore, qmltc-compiled apps using Qt's QML modules will require linking against private Qt API, see also <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-qml-type-compiler.xml#compiling-qml-code-with-qmltc">Compiling QML code with qmltc</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:para>If a QML module has <db:code>.qml</db:code> files, you can compile them to C++ using <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-qml-type-compiler.xml">qmltc</db:link>. Unlike <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#qmlcachegen-auto">bytecode compilation</db:link>, you have to explicitly enable qmltc via <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#enable-type-compiler">ENABLE_TYPE_COMPILER</db:link> argument. In which case, <db:code>.qml</db:code> files specified under <db:code>QML_FILES</db:code> would be compiled. Files ending with <db:code>.js</db:code> and <db:code>.mjs</db:code> are ignored as qmltc does not compile JavaScript code. Additionally, files marked with QT_QML_SKIP_TYPE_COMPILER source file property are also skipped.</db:para>
<db:para>By default, qmltc creates lower-case <db:code>.h</db:code> and <db:code>.cpp</db:code> files for a given <db:code>.qml</db:code> file. For example, <db:code>Foo.qml</db:code> ends up being compiled into <db:code>foo.h</db:code> and <db:code>foo.cpp</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:para>The created C++ files are placed into a dedicated <db:code>.qmltc/&lt;target&gt;/</db:code> sub-directory of the <db:code>BINARY_DIR</db:code> of the <db:code>target</db:code>. These files are then automatically added to the target sources and compiled as Qt C++ code along with other source files.</db:para>
<db:para>While processing QML_FILES, the following source file properties are respected:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:code>QT_QMLTC_FILE_BASENAME</db:code>: use this source file property to specify a non-default .h and .cpp file name, which might be useful to e.g. resolve conflicting file names (imagine you have main.qml that is being compiled, but main.h already exists, so #include &quot;main.h&quot; might not do what you expect it to do). QT_QMLTC_FILE_BASENAME is expected to be a file name (without extension), so any preceding directory is ignored. Unlike in the case of default behavior, the QT_QMLTC_FILE_BASENAME is not lower-cased.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:code>QT_QML_SKIP_TYPE_COMPILER</db:code>: use this source file property to specify that a QML file must be ignored by qmltc.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="arguments">
<db:title>Arguments</db:title>
<db:section xml:id="required-arguments">
<db:title>Required arguments</db:title>
<db:para>The <db:code>target</db:code> specifies the name of the backing target for the QML module. By default, it is created as a shared library if Qt was built as shared libraries, or as a static library otherwise. This choice can be explicitly overridden with the <db:code>STATIC</db:code> or <db:code>SHARED</db:code> options.</db:para>
<db:para>Every QML module must define a <db:code>URI</db:code>. It should be specified in dotted URI notation, such as <db:code>QtQuick.Layouts</db:code>. Each segment must be a well-formed ECMAScript Identifier Name. This means, for example, the segments must not start with a number and they must not contain <db:emphasis>-</db:emphasis> (minus) characters. As the <db:code>URI</db:code> will be translated into directory names, you should restrict it to alphanumeric characters of the latin alphabet, underscores, and dots. Other QML modules may use this name in <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-syntax-imports.xml">import statements</db:link> to import the module. The <db:code>URI</db:code> will be used in the <db:code>module</db:code> line of the generated <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file. The <db:code>URI</db:code> is also used to form the <db:emphasis>target path</db:emphasis> by replacing dots with forward slashes.</db:para>
<db:para>See <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-identifiedmodules.xml">Identified Modules</db:link> for further in-depth discussion of the module URI.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="versions">
<db:title>Versions</db:title>
<db:para>A QML module can also define a <db:code>VERSION</db:code> in the form <db:code>Major.Minor</db:code>, where both <db:code>Major</db:code> and <db:code>Minor</db:code> must be integers. An additional <db:code>.Patch</db:code> component may be appended, but will be ignored. A list of earlier major versions the module provides types for can also optionally be given after the <db:code>PAST_MAJOR_VERSIONS</db:code> keyword (see below). See <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-identifiedmodules.xml">Identified Modules</db:link> for further in-depth discussion of version numbering, <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#registering-past-major-versions">Registering past major versions</db:link> for registering past major versions, and <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#keeping-module-versions-in-sync">Keeping module versions in sync</db:link> for keeping module versions in sync.</db:para>
<db:para>If you don't need versions you should omit the <db:code>VERSION</db:code> argument. It defaults to the highest possible version. Internal versioning of QML modules has some fundamental flaws. You should use an external package management mechanism to manage different versions of your QML modules.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="adding-sources-and-resources-to-the-module">
<db:title>Adding sources and resources to the module</db:title>
<db:para><db:code>SOURCES</db:code> specifies a list of non-QML sources to be added to the backing target. It is provided as a convenience and is equivalent to adding the sources to the backing target with the built-in <db:code>target_sources()</db:code> CMake command.</db:para>
<db:para><db:code>QML_FILES</db:code> lists the <db:code>.qml</db:code>, <db:code>.js</db:code> and <db:code>.mjs</db:code> files for the module. These will be automatically <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#qmlcachegen-auto">compiled into bytecode</db:link> and embedded in the backing target unless the <db:code>NO_CACHEGEN</db:code> option is given. The uncompiled file is always stored in the embedded resources of the backing target, even if <db:code>NO_CACHEGEN</db:code> is specified. Unless the <db:code>NO_LINT</db:code> option is given, the uncompiled files will also be <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#linting-qml-sources">processed by <db:code>qmllint</db:code></db:link> via a separate custom build target. The files will also be used to populate type information in the generated <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file by default. <db:code>NO_GENERATE_QMLDIR</db:code> can be given to disable the automatic generation of the <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file. This should normally be avoided, but for cases where the project needs to provide its own <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file, this option can be used.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>See <db:link xlink:href="qt-target-qml-sources.xml#qt6-target-qml-sources">qt_target_qml_sources()</db:link> for further details on how to add qmlfiles after <db:code>qt_add_qml_module()</db:code> was called. For example, you may wish to add files conditionally based on an if statement expression, or from subdirectories that will only be added if certain criteria are met. Furthermore, files added with <db:link xlink:href="qt-target-qml-sources.xml#qt6-target-qml-sources">qt_target_qml_sources()</db:link> also can specify if they should be skipped for the linting, <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#qmlcachegen-auto">bytecode compilation</db:link> or <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file generation.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:para><db:code>RESOURCES</db:code> lists any other files needed by the module, such as images referenced from the QML code. These files will be added as compiled-in resources (see <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#resource-prefix">RESOURCE_PREFIX</db:link> for an explanation of the base point they will be located under). If needed, their relative location can be controlled by setting the <db:code>QT_RESOURCE_ALIAS</db:code> source property, just as for <db:code>.qml</db:code> files (see <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#qmlcachegen-auto">Caching compiled QML sources</db:link>).</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="resource-prefix"/>
<db:para><db:code>RESOURCE_PREFIX</db:code> is intended to encapsulate a namespace for the project and will often be the same for all QML modules that the project defines. It should be chosen to avoid clashing with the resource prefix of anything else used by the project or likely to be used by any other project that might consume it. A good choice is to incorporate the domain name of the organization the project belongs to. A common convention is to append <db:code>/imports</db:code> to the domain name to form the resource prefix. For example:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">qt_add_qml_module(someTarget
    RESOURCE_PREFIX /my.company.com/imports
    ...
)
</db:programlisting>
<db:anchor xml:id="no-resource-target-path"/>
<db:para>When various files are added to the compiled-in resources, they are placed under a path formed by concatenating the <db:code>RESOURCE_PREFIX</db:code> and the target path. For the special case where the backing target is an executable, it may be desirable to place the module's <db:code>.qml</db:code> files and other resources directly under the <db:code>RESOURCE_PREFIX</db:code> instead. This can be achieved by specifying the <db:code>NO_RESOURCE_TARGET_PATH</db:code> option, which may only be used if the backing target is an executable.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="past-major-versions"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="registering-past-major-versions">
<db:title>Registering past major versions</db:title>
<db:para><db:code>PAST_MAJOR_VERSIONS</db:code> contains a list of additional major version that the module provides. For each of those versions and each QML file without a <db:code>QT_QML_SOURCE_VERSIONS</db:code> setting an additional entry in the <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file will be generated to specify the extra version. Furthermore, the generated module registration code will register the past major versions using <db:link xlink:href="qqmlengine.xml#qmlRegisterModule">qmlRegisterModule</db:link>() on the C++ side. The module registration code is automatically generated for your QML module, unless you specify <db:code>NO_GENERATE_QMLTYPES</db:code> (but use of this option is strongly discouraged). Usage of <db:code>PAST_MAJOR_VERSIONS</db:code> adds some overhead when your module is imported. You should increment the major version of your module as rarely as possible. Once you can rely on all QML files importing this module to omit the version in their imports, you can safely omit <db:code>PAST_MAJOR_VERSIONS</db:code>. All the QML files will then import the latest version of your module. If you have to support versioned imports, consider supporting only a limited number of past major versions.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="declaring-module-dependencies">
<db:title>Declaring module dependencies</db:title>
<db:para><db:code>IMPORTS</db:code> provides a list of other QML modules that this module imports. Each module listed here will be added as an <db:code>import</db:code> entry in the generated <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file. If a QML file imports this module, it also imports all the modules listed under <db:code>IMPORTS</db:code>. Optionally, a version can be specified by appending it after a slash, such as <db:code>QtQuick/2.0</db:code>. Omitting the version will cause the greatest version available to be imported. You may only specify the major version, as in <db:code>QtQuick/2</db:code>. In that case the greatest minor version available with the given major version will be imported. Finally, <db:code>auto</db:code> may be given as version (<db:code>QtQuick/auto</db:code>). If <db:code>auto</db:code> is given, the version that the current module is being imported with is propagated to the module to be imported. Given an entry <db:code>QtQuick/auto</db:code> in a module <db:code>YourModule</db:code>, if a QML file specifies <db:code>import YourModule 3.14</db:code>, this results in importing version <db:code>3.14</db:code> of <db:code>QtQuick</db:code>. For related modules that follow a common versioning scheme, you should use <db:code>auto</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:para><db:code>OPTIONAL_IMPORTS</db:code> provides a list of other QML modules that this module <db:emphasis>may</db:emphasis> import at run-time. These are not automatically imported by the QML engine when importing the current module, but rather serve as hints to tools like <db:code>qmllint</db:code>. Versions can be specified in the same way as for <db:code>IMPORTS</db:code>. Each module listed here will be added as an <db:code>optional import</db:code> entry in the generated <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file.</db:para>
<db:para><db:code>DEFAULT_IMPORTS</db:code> specifies which of the optional imports are the default entries that should be loaded by tooling. One entry should be specified for every group of <db:code>OPTIONAL_IMPORTS</db:code> in the module. As optional imports are only resolved at runtime, tooling like qmllint cannot in general know which of the optional imports should be resolved. To remedy this, you can specify one of the optional imports as the default import; tooling will then pick it. If you have one optional import that gets used at runtime without any further configuration, that is an ideal candidate for the default import.</db:para>
<db:para><db:code>DEPENDENCIES</db:code> provides a list of other QML modules that this module depends on, but doesn't necessarily import. It would typically be used for dependencies that only exist at the C++ level, such as a module registering a class to QML which is a subclass of one defined in another module.</db:para>
<db:para>For example, if one would like to subclass <db:code>QQuickItem</db:code> as following:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">class MyItem: public QQuickItem { ... };
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>then one has to make sure that the module containing <db:code>QQuickItem</db:code>, called <db:code>Quick</db:code>, is declared as a dependency via the <db:code>DEPENDENCIES</db:code> option. Not doing so might result in errors during type compilation with <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-qml-type-compiler.xml">qmltc</db:link> or during binding and function compilation to C++ with <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#qmlcachegen-auto">qmlcachegen</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Adding the module to <db:code>DEPENDENCIES</db:code> is not necessary if the module is already imported via the <db:code>IMPORTS</db:code> option. The recommended way is to use the lighter alternative <db:code>DEPENDENCIES</db:code> over <db:code>IMPORTS</db:code>.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:para>The module version of the dependencies must be specified along with the module name, in the same form as used for <db:code>IMPORTS</db:code> and <db:code>OPTIONAL_IMPORTS</db:code>. Each module listed here will be added as a <db:code>depends</db:code> entry in the generated <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="import-path"/>
<db:para><db:code>IMPORT_PATH</db:code> can be used to add to the search paths where other QML modules that this one depends on can be found. The other modules must have their <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file under their own target path below one of the search paths.</db:para>
<db:para>If the backing target is a static library and that static library will be installed, <db:code>OUTPUT_TARGETS</db:code> should be given to provide a variable in which to store a list of additional targets that will also need to be installed. These additional targets are generated internally by <db:code>qt_add_qml_module()</db:code> and are referenced by the backing target's linking requirements as part of ensuring that resources are set up and loaded correctly.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="plugin-target"/>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="targets-and-plugin-targets">
<db:title>Targets and plugin targets</db:title>
<db:para><db:code>PLUGIN_TARGET</db:code> specifies the plugin target associated with the QML module. The <db:code>PLUGIN_TARGET</db:code> can be the same as the backing <db:code>target</db:code>, in which case there will be no separate backing target. If <db:code>PLUGIN_TARGET</db:code> is not given, it defaults to <db:code>target</db:code> with <db:code>plugin</db:code> appended. For example, a backing target called <db:code>mymodule</db:code> would have a default plugin name of <db:code>mymoduleplugin</db:code>. The plugin target's name will be used to populate a <db:code>plugin</db:code> line in the generated <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file. Therefore, you must not try to change the plugin's output name by setting target properties like <db:code>OUTPUT_NAME</db:code> or any of its related properties.</db:para>
<db:para>The backing <db:code>target</db:code> and the plugin target (if different) will be created by the command, unless they already exist. Projects should generally let them be created by the command so that they are created as the appropriate target type. If the backing <db:code>target</db:code> is a static library, the plugin will also be created as a static library. If the backing <db:code>target</db:code> is a shared library, the plugin will be created as a module library. If an existing <db:code>target</db:code> is passed in and it is an executable target, there will be no plugin. If you intend to always link directly to the backing target and do not need a plugin, it can be disabled by adding the <db:code>NO_PLUGIN</db:code> option. Specifying both <db:code>NO_PLUGIN</db:code> and <db:code>PLUGIN_TARGET</db:code> is an error.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="no-create-plugin-target"/>
<db:para>In certain situations, the project may want to delay creating the plugin target until after the call. The <db:code>NO_CREATE_PLUGIN_TARGET</db:code> option can be given in that situation. The project is then expected to call <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-plugin.xml#qt6-add-qml-plugin">qt_add_qml_plugin()</db:link> on the plugin target once it has been created. When <db:code>NO_CREATE_PLUGIN_TARGET</db:code> is given, <db:code>PLUGIN_TARGET</db:code> must also be provided to explicitly name the plugin target.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="class-name"/>
<db:anchor xml:id="no-generate-plugin-source"/>
<db:para>By default, <db:code>qt_add_qml_module()</db:code> will auto-generate a <db:code>.cpp</db:code> file that implements the plugin class named by the <db:code>CLASS_NAME</db:code> argument. The generated <db:code>.cpp</db:code> file will be automatically added to the plugin target as a source file to be compiled. If the project wants to provide its own implementation of the plugin class, the <db:code>NO_GENERATE_PLUGIN_SOURCE</db:code> option should be given. Where no <db:code>CLASS_NAME</db:code> is provided, it defaults to the <db:code>URI</db:code> with dots replaced by underscores, then <db:code>Plugin</db:code> appended. Unless the QML module has no plugin, the class name will be recorded as a <db:code>classname</db:code> line in the generated <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file. You need to add any C++ files with custom plugin code to the plugin target. Since the plugin then likely contains functionality that goes beyond simply loading the backing library, you will probably want to add <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#no-plugin-optional">NO_PLUGIN_OPTIONAL</db:link>, too. Otherwise the QML engine may skip loading the plugin if it detects that the backing library is already linked.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="no-plugin"/>
<db:para>If the <db:code>NO_PLUGIN</db:code> keyword is given, then no plugin will be built. This keyword is thus incompatible with all the options that customize the plugin target, in particular <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#no-generate-plugin-source">NO_GENERATE_PLUGIN_SOURCE</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#no-plugin-optional">NO_PLUGIN_OPTIONAL</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#plugin-target">PLUGIN_TARGET</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#no-create-plugin-target">NO_CREATE_PLUGIN_TARGET</db:link>, and <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#class-name">CLASS_NAME</db:link>. If you do not provide a plugin for your module, it will only be fully usable if its backing library has been linked into the executable. It is generally hard to guarantee that a linker preserves the linkage to a library it considers unused.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="no-plugin-optional"/>
<db:para>If the <db:code>NO_PLUGIN_OPTIONAL</db:code> keyword is given, then the plugin is recorded in the generated <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file as non-optional. If all of a QML module's functionality is implemented in its backing target and the plugin target is separate, then the plugin can be optional, which is the default and recommended arrangement. The auto-generated plugin source file satisfies this requirement. Where a project provides its own <db:code>.cpp</db:code> implementation for the plugin, that would normally mean the <db:code>NO_PLUGIN_OPTIONAL</db:code> keyword is also needed because the plugin will almost certainly contain functionality that the QML module requires.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="automatic-type-registration">
<db:title>Automatic type registration</db:title>
<db:para>Type registration is automatically performed for the backing target's C++ sources that are processed by AUTOMOC. This will generate a typeinfo file in the <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#output-directory">output directory</db:link>, the file name being the <db:code>target</db:code> name with <db:code>.qmltypes</db:code> appended. This file name can be changed using the <db:code>TYPEINFO</db:code> option if desired, but this should not normally be necessary. The file name is also recorded as a <db:code>typeinfo</db:code> entry in the generated <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">qmldir</db:link> file. Automatic type registration can be disabled using the <db:code>NO_GENERATE_QMLTYPES</db:code> option, in which case no typeinfo file will be generated, but the project will still be expected to generate a typeinfo file and place it in the same directory as the generated <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="output-directory"/>
<db:para><db:code>OUTPUT_DIRECTORY</db:code> specifies where the plugin library, <db:code>qmldir</db:code> and typeinfo files are generated. When this keyword is not given, the default value will be the target path (formed from the <db:code>URI</db:code>) appended to the value of the <db:link xlink:href="cmake-variable-qt-qml-output-directory.xml">QT_QML_OUTPUT_DIRECTORY</db:link> variable. If that variable is not defined, the default depends on the type of backing target. For executables, the value will be the target path appended to <db:code>${CMAKE_CURRENT_BINARY_DIR}</db:code>, whereas for other targets it will be just <db:code>${CMAKE_CURRENT_BINARY_DIR}</db:code>. When the structure of the source tree matches the structure of QML module target paths (which is highly recommended), <db:link xlink:href="cmake-variable-qt-qml-output-directory.xml">QT_QML_OUTPUT_DIRECTORY</db:link> often isn't needed. In order to match the structure of the target paths, you have to call your directories <db:emphasis>exactly</db:emphasis> like the segments of your module URI. For example, if your module URI is <db:code>MyUpperCaseThing.mylowercasething</db:code>, you need to put this in a directory called <db:code>MyUpperCaseThing/mylowercasething/</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:para>The need for specifying the <db:code>OUTPUT_DIRECTORY</db:code> keyword should be rare, but if it is used, it is likely that the caller will also need to add to the <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#import-path">IMPORT_PATH</db:link> to ensure that <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#qmllint-auto">linting</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qt-add-qml-module.xml#qmlcachegen-auto">cached compilation</db:link> of qml sources, <db:link xlink:href="qt-import-qml-plugins.xml#qt6-import-qml-plugins">automatic importing</db:link> of plugins in static builds, and <db:link xlink:href="qt-deploy-qml-imports.xml">deploying imported QML modules</db:link> for non-static builds all work correctly.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="qt-quick-designer-compatibility">
<db:title>Qt Quick Designer compatibility</db:title>
<db:para><db:code>DESIGNER_SUPPORTED</db:code> should be given if the QML module supports Qt Quick Designer. When present, the generated <db:code>qmldir</db:code> file will contain a <db:code>designersupported</db:code> line. See <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-modules-qmldir.xml">Module Definition qmldir Files</db:link> for how this affects the way Qt Quick Designer handles the plugin.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="keeping-module-versions-in-sync">
<db:title>Keeping module versions in sync</db:title>
<db:para>The <db:code>FOLLOW_FOREIGN_VERSIONING</db:code> keyword relates to base types of your own C++-defined QML types that live in different QML modules. Typically, the versioning scheme of your module does not match that of the module providing the base types. Therefore, by default all revisions of the base types are made available in any import of your module. If <db:code>FOLLOW_FOREIGN_VERSIONING</db:code> is given, the version information attached to the base types and their properties is respected. So, an <db:code>import MyModule 2.8</db:code> will then only make available versioned properties up to version <db:code>2.8</db:code> of any base types outside <db:code>MyModule</db:code>. This is mostly useful if you want to keep your module version in sync with other modules you're basing types on. In that case you might want your custom types to not expose properties from a module's base type version greater than the one being imported.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="c-namespaces-of-generated-code">
<db:title>C++ namespaces of generated code</db:title>
<db:para>If a namespace is given with the <db:code>NAMESPACE</db:code> keyword, the plugin and registration code will be generated into a C++ namespace of this name.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="qmlimportscanner-and-no-import-scan">
<db:title>qmlimportscanner and NO_IMPORT_SCAN</db:title>
<db:para>For static Qt builds, <db:code>qmlimportscanner</db:code> is run at configure time to scan the <db:code>.qml</db:code> files of a QML module and identify the QML imports it uses (see <db:link xlink:href="qt-import-qml-plugins.xml#qt6-import-qml-plugins">qt_import_qml_plugins()</db:link>). For non-static Qt builds, if the target is an executable, a similar scan is performed at build time to provide the information needed by deployment scripts (see <db:link xlink:href="qt-deploy-qml-imports.xml">qt_deploy_qml_imports()</db:link>). Both scans can be disabled by providing the <db:code>NO_IMPORT_SCAN</db:code> option. Doing so means the project takes on the responsibility of ensuring all required plugins are instantiated and linked for static builds. For non-static builds the project must manually work out and deploy all QML modules used by an executable target.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="arguments-for-qmltc">
<db:title>Arguments for qmltc</db:title>
<db:anchor xml:id="enable-type-compiler"/>
<db:para><db:code>ENABLE_TYPE_COMPILER</db:code> can be used to compile <db:code>.qml</db:code> files to C++ source code with <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-qml-type-compiler.xml">qmltc</db:link>. Files with the source property <db:code>QT_QML_SKIP_TYPE_COMPILER</db:code> are not compiled to C++.</db:para>
<db:para><db:code>TYPE_COMPILER_NAMESPACE</db:code> argument allows to override the namespace in which <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-qml-type-compiler.xml">qmltc</db:link> generates code. By default, the namespace of the generated code follows the module hierarchy as depicted in the URI, e.g., <db:code>MyModule</db:code> for a module with URI <db:code>MyModule</db:code> or <db:code>com::example::Module</db:code> for URI <db:code>com.example.MyModule</db:code>. By specifying the <db:code>TYPE_COMPILER_NAMESPACE</db:code> option, the generated code can be put instead in a custom namespace, where different subnamespaces are to be separated by a &quot;::&quot;, e.g. &quot;MyNamespace::MySubnamespace&quot; for the namespace MySubnamespace that is inside the MyNamespace. Apart from the &quot;::&quot;, C++ namespace naming rules apply.</db:para>
<db:para><db:code>QMLTC_QMLTC_EXPORT_DIRECTIVE</db:code> should be used with <db:code>QMLTC_EXPORT_FILE_NAME</db:code> when the classes generated by <db:link xlink:href="qtqml-qml-type-compiler.xml">qmltc</db:link> should be exported from the qml library. By default, classes generated by qmltc are not exported from their library. The header defining the export macro for the current library can be specified as an optional argument to <db:code>QMLTC_EXPORT_FILE_NAME</db:code> while the exporting macro name should be specified as an argument to <db:code>QMLTC_QMLTC_EXPORT_DIRECTIVE</db:code>. If no additional include is required or wanted, e.g. when the header of the export macro is already indirectly included by a base class, then the <db:code>QMLTC_EXPORT_FILE_NAME</db:code> option can be left out.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
</db:article>
