<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Get and Install Qt with Qt Online Installer</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.5.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Downloading and installing the Qt modules and tools that you need.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-02-14</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-02-14</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>The Qt Online Installer gives you the choice of installing only the modules and tools you need to develop on a particular desktop platform and to run your applications on one or several desktop platforms, mobile or embedded devices, or MCUs.</db:para>
<db:para>If instead you prefer to build Qt from sources, please see <db:link xlink:href="build-sources.xml">Building Qt Sources</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="A1-create-a-qt-account">
<db:title>1. Create a Qt Account</db:title>
<db:para>To begin, create a <db:link xlink:href="https://account.qt.io/">Qt Account</db:link>. This account gives you access to a web portal where you can manage your licenses, as well as access to the forums and wikis. Also, make sure you read the <db:link xlink:href="licensing.xml">Qt Licensing</db:link> page regarding your chosen license.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="A2-download-the-installer">
<db:title>2. Download the Installer</db:title>
<db:para>Go to your Qt account's download page. By selecting the appropriate unified Qt online installer for your OS, you can install commercial or open source versions of Qt, development tools, and other components. The online installer asks for your Qt account credentials. The installer retrieves the license attached to the account from a server and provides a list of available components corresponding to the license.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="A3-install-qt">
<db:title>3. Install Qt</db:title>
<db:para>To complete the installation, select the components that you want to install and follow the instructions of the installation program.</db:para>
<db:para>You must select at least one Qt version for one platform that you want to run your applications on. For example, if you have installed Microsoft Visual Studio 2022 on 64-bit Windows, you could select <db:emphasis>MSVC 2022 64-bit</db:emphasis> under the Qt version you want to develop with.</db:para>
<db:para>However, the easiest way to install Qt for desktop development is to select the default installation for desktop development. You can install additional modules later.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/qtinstallercomponents.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>If you also want to run your applications on Android devices, for example, you should select the default installation for mobile development.</db:para>
<db:para>The following table contains examples of which components to install depending on the platforms where you want to run your applications.</db:para>
<db:informaltable style="generic">
<db:thead>
<db:tr>
<db:th>
<db:para>To Develop For</db:para>
</db:th>
<db:th>
<db:para>Choose</db:para>
</db:th>
</db:tr>
</db:thead>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>Desktop</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>Default installation for <db:emphasis>desktop development</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
<db:para>If you want to use other than the default toolchain, such as MSVC on Windows, select <db:emphasis>Custom installation</db:emphasis>. Then select the Qt for the toolchain you want to use.</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>Mobile Devices</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>Default installation for <db:emphasis>mobile development</db:emphasis>.</db:para>
<db:para>If you only want to develop for a particular platform, select <db:emphasis>Custom installation</db:emphasis>. Then select the Qt for the mobile device platform that you want to run the applications on. For example, <db:link xlink:href="android.xml">Qt for Android</db:link> or <db:link xlink:href="ios.xml">Qt for iOS</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>Embedded Devices</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>Custom installation, with the necessary Qt modules and toolchains from the <db:link xlink:href="https://doc.qt.io/Boot2Qt/">Boot to Qt</db:link> section, depending on the types of devices that you want to run applications on.</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>Android Automotive</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>Custom installation, with <db:link xlink:href="https://doc.qt.io/QtAndroidAutomotive/">Qt for Android Automotive</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>Automation</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>Custom installation, with the necessary Qt modules and toolchains from the <db:link xlink:href="http://doc.qt.io/QtForAutomation/index.html">Qt for Automation/Qt M2M Protocols</db:link> section, depending on the types of devices that you want to run applications on.</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
<db:tr valign="top">
<db:td>
<db:para>MCUs</db:para>
</db:td>
<db:td>
<db:para>Custom installation, with <db:link xlink:href="https://doc.qt.io/QtForMCUs">Qt for MCUs</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:td>
</db:tr>
</db:informaltable>
<db:para>To check the platform requirements, see <db:link xlink:href="supported-platforms.xml">Supported Platforms</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:para>The following YouTube video gives a complete walk-through of the installation process:</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:videoobject>
<?db video="iframe"?>
<db:videodata format="youtube" fileref="yIv0vO8B7tQ">
</db:videodata>
</db:videoobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/yIv0vO8B7tQ.jpg">
</db:imagedata>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:section xml:id="updating-or-removing-components">
<db:title>Updating or Removing Components</db:title>
<db:para>Once Qt is installed, you can use the <db:emphasis>Maintenance Tool</db:emphasis> under <db:emphasis>&lt;install_dir&gt;</db:emphasis> to add components, update, or remove installed components.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="getting-help">
<db:title>Getting Help</db:title>
<db:para>Evaluation and open source users can get help on the <db:link xlink:href="https://forum.qt.io/">Qt forum</db:link>. See also the <db:link xlink:href="https://wiki.qt.io/Forum_Help">Help on using the Forum</db:link> wiki page.</db:para>
<db:para>Non-commercial users can get limited help with the installation process through <db:link xlink:href="https://account.qt.io/support">Qt support</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:para>The primary support channel for commercial customers is their <db:link xlink:href="https://account.qt.io/support">Qt Account</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="A4-create-applications">
<db:title>4. Create Applications</db:title>
<db:para>After the installation, <db:link xlink:href="https://doc.qt.io/qtcreator/index.html">Qt Creator</db:link> opens. You can use the project wizard templates to start creating applications that run on your chosen platform.</db:para>
<db:para>If you want to design Qt Quick UIs, open <db:link xlink:href="https://doc.qt.io/qtdesignstudio/index.html">Qt Design Studio</db:link> and use the project wizard templates there.</db:para>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="create-your-first-applications.xml">Tell me more</db:link></db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="additional-resources">
<db:title>Additional Resources</db:title>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://www.qt.io/courses">Qt Learning</db:link> has a course on <db:link xlink:href="https://www.qt.io/courses/how-to-install-qt?hsLang=en">how to install Qt</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
