<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Changes to Qt3D</db:title>
<db:productname>Qt3D</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.8.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt 3D Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt 3D Reference Documentation.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>Qt 6 is a result of the conscious effort to make the framework more efficient and easy to use.</db:para>
<db:para>We try to maintain binary and source compatibility for all the public APIs in each release. But some changes were inevitable in an effort to make Qt a better framework.</db:para>
<db:para>In this topic we summarize those changes in Qt3D, and provide guidance to handle them.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="new-rendering-backend">
<db:title>New rendering backend</db:title>
<db:para>Over the course of 5.14 and 5.15, the rendering backend was gradually moved into a plugin.</db:para>
<db:para>Qt 6 release completes this work and introduces a new RHI based rendering backend which will enable use of Vulkan, Metal or DirectX on the relevant platforms.</db:para>
<db:para>The RHI backend is the default but this can be controlled by setting environment variables as explained <db:link xlink:href="qt3drender-module.xml" role="deprecated">here</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="code-changes">
<db:title>Code changes</db:title>
<db:para>Some classes have changed modules. In particular, the QBuffer, QAttribute and QGeometry classes (along with associated helper classes) have moved from the Render module to the Core module.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="new-api">
<db:title>New API</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qt3dcore-qgeometryview.xml">Qt3DCore::QGeometryView</db:link> provides all details for a mesh</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qt3dcore-qboundingvolume.xml">Qt3DCore::QBoundingVolume</db:link> provides a way of querying or overriding the size of the axis aligned bounding box of a geometry</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qt3drender-qpickingproxy.xml">Qt3DRender::QPickingProxy</db:link> provides a way of specifying an alternative (usually simpler) geometry for picking</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qt3dcore-qabstractaspect.xml">Qt3DCore::QAbstractAspect</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="qt3dcore-qaspectjob.xml">Qt3DCore::QAspectJob</db:link> add methods to facilitate and optimize the synchronization of backend operations.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
</db:article>
