<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Data Compression Library (zlib), version 1.3</db:title>
<db:productname>QtCore</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.5.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Core Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>zlib License.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-02-14</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-02-14</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:anchor xml:id="zlib"/>
<db:para>zlib is a general purpose data compression library.</db:para>
<db:para>Optionally used in Qt Core and development tools. Configure with -system-zlib to avoid.</db:para>
<db:para>The sources can be found in qtbase/src/3rdparty/zlib.</db:para>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://zlib.net/">Project Homepage</db:link>, upstream version: <db:link xlink:href="https://www.zlib.net/zlib-1.3.tar.gz">1.3</db:link></db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">(C) 1995-2023 Jean-loup Gailly and Mark Adler
</db:programlisting>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://spdx.org/licenses/Zlib.html">zlib License</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">This software is provided 'as-is', without any express or implied
  warranty.  In no event will the authors be held liable for any damages
  arising from the use of this software.

  Permission is granted to anyone to use this software for any purpose,
  including commercial applications, and to alter it and redistribute it
  freely, subject to the following restrictions:

  1. The origin of this software must not be misrepresented; you must not
     claim that you wrote the original software. If you use this software
     in a product, an acknowledgment in the product documentation would be
     appreciated but is not required.
  2. Altered source versions must be plainly marked as such, and must not be
     misrepresented as being the original software.
  3. This notice may not be removed or altered from any source distribution.

  Jean-loup Gailly        Mark Adler
  jloup@gzip.org          madler@alumni.caltech.edu

If you use the zlib library in a product, we would appreciate *not* receiving
lengthy legal documents to sign.  The sources are provided for free but without
warranty of any kind.  The library has been entirely written by Jean-loup
Gailly and Mark Adler; it does not include third-party code.

If you redistribute modified sources, we would appreciate that you include in
the file ChangeLog history information documenting your changes.  Please read
the FAQ for more information on the distribution of modified source versions.
</db:programlisting>
</db:article>
