<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt Data Visualization Interacting with Data</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDataVisualization</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.7.1 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Data Visualization Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt Data Visualization Reference Documentation.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:section xml:id="interacting-with-data">
<db:title>Interacting with data</db:title>
<db:para>You can interact with the rendered graph with either mouse or touch to rotate, zoom, or select data. For the default mouse controls, see Q3DInputHandler documentation, and for the default touch controls, see QTouch3DInputHandler documentation.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="data-selection-modes">
<db:title>Data selection modes</db:title>
<db:para>All visualization types support selecting a single data item - a bar, a scatter item, or a surface vertex - using mouse, touch, and programmatically via the series APIs. The selected item is highlighted in the rendered graph, and selecting causes emission of a series specific signal for this purpose, for example, QBar3DSeries::selectedBarChanged(), which the application can handle.</db:para>
<db:para>Bar and surface graphs support slice selection modes, where the selected row or column is drawn in a separate viewport as a pseudo-2D graph. This makes it easier to see the actual values of a single row or column.</db:para>
<db:para>Bar graph additionally supports simply highlighting the whole row and/or column of the selected bar without opening the slice view. Bar graph also supports selecting/slicing a whole row and/or column by clicking the axis label, based on selection mode.</db:para>
<db:para>When multiple series are added to a graph, selecting an item in one of them will clear the selection on other series.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
