<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Changes to Qt Location</db:title>
<db:productname>QtLocation</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.7.2 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Location Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Migrate Qt Location to Qt 6.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>Qt 6 is a result of the conscious effort to make the framework more efficient and easy to use.</db:para>
<db:para>We try to maintain binary and source compatibility for all the public APIs in each release. But some changes were inevitable in an effort to make Qt a better framework.</db:para>
<db:para>In this topic we summarize those changes in Qt Location, and provide guidance to handle them.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="breaking-public-api-changes">
<db:title>Breaking public API changes</db:title>
<db:section xml:id="maps">
<db:title>Maps</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The MapRectangle::backend, MapCircle::backend, MapPolyline::backend, and MapPolygon::backend properties have been removed.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The former Routing-related QML element types Route, RouteSegment, and RouteManeuver are now value types <db:link xlink:href="qml-route.xml">route</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtlocation-routesegment.xml">routeSegment</db:link>, and <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtlocation-routemaneuver.xml">routeManeuver</db:link>. They can no longer be instantiated as items in QML, and their properties can not be bound to.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The former Mapping-related QML element types MapType and CameraCapabilities are now value types <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtlocation-maptype.xml">mapType</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="qml-cameracapabilities.xml">cameraCapabilities</db:link>. They can no longer be instantiated as items in QML, and their properties can not be bound to.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QGeoRouteLeg class and the QML equivalent, RouteLeg, have been merged into <db:link xlink:href="qgeoroute.xml">QGeoRoute</db:link> (and the <db:link xlink:href="qml-route.xml">route</db:link> type). A route can be an aggregate of several routes.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtlocation-map.xml">Map</db:link> type provides now minimal functionality without handling of user intput. The MapGestureArea was removed. The <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtlocation-mapview.xml">MapView</db:link> type handles basic user input such as tap and drag events.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="places">
<db:title>Places</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QPlaceImage, QPlaceEditorial, and QPlaceReview classes have been folded into <db:link xlink:href="qplacecontent.xml">QPlaceContent</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The <db:link xlink:href="qplacecontent.xml">QPlaceContent</db:link> API has been changed to give access to a list of <db:link xlink:href="qvariant.xml">QVariant</db:link> values.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The former QML element types PlaceUser, PlaceRatings, PlaceAttribute, PlaceIcon, PlaceSupplier, and PlaceContactDetail are now value types <db:link xlink:href="qml-user.xml">user</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qml-ratings.xml">ratings</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qml-placeattribute.xml">placeAttribute</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qml-icon.xml">icon</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qml-supplier.xml">supplier</db:link>, and <db:link xlink:href="qml-contactdetail.xml">contactDetail</db:link>. They can no longer be instantiated as items from QML, and their properties can not be bound to.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="experimental-apis">
<db:title>Experimental APIs</db:title>
<db:para>Functionality that had &quot;labs&quot; status has been removed. This includes the experimental framework for turn-by-turn navigation, as well as the MapObjects abstraction.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="backend-provider-api">
<db:title>Backend Provider API</db:title>
<db:para>The backend provider API is no longer subject to binary and source compatibility guarantees.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="other-api-changes">
<db:title>Other API changes</db:title>
<db:para>This section contains API improvements that do not break source compatibility. However they might have an impact on the application logic, so it is still useful to know about them.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
