<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Spectrum Example</db:title>
<db:productname>QtMultimedia</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.4.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Multimedia Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Analyzing a raw audio stream using the FFTReal library.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-01-26</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-01-26</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para><db:emphasis>Spectrum</db:emphasis> demonstrates how the <db:link xlink:href="qtmultimedia-index.xml">Qt Multimedia</db:link> module can be used to analyze an audio stream while recording it, and also play the recorded stream.</db:para>
<db:mediaobject>
<db:imageobject>
<db:imagedata fileref="images/spectrum-demo.png"/>
</db:imageobject>
</db:mediaobject>
<db:para>Because Qt Multimedia allows the application to access the raw audio stream, the data can either be inspected or modified by the application. The Spectrum Analyzer example displays three pieces of information while audio is being either captured or played back:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>Information about the raw audio stream, shown in the uppermost widget:</db:para>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The amount of data currently in the buffer, shown in blue</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The segment of data which was most recently analysed to compute the frequency spectrum, shown in green</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The raw audio waveform, shown in white and scrolling from right to left</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>A representation of the frequency spectrum, shown at the lower left</db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The current RMS level of the audio stream, and the recent 'high watermark' level, shown at the lower right</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
<db:para>Spectrum analysis is performed by calculating the Fast Fourier Transform (FFT) of a segment of audio data. An open-source library, <db:link xlink:href="http://ldesoras.free.fr/prod.html">FFTReal</db:link> is used to compute the transform. FFTReal is available under the GNU Library General Public License 2.0 or later.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="running-the-example">
<db:title>Running the Example</db:title>
<db:para>To run the example from <db:link xlink:href="https://doc.qt.io/qtcreator/index.html">Qt Creator</db:link>, open the <db:guilabel>Welcome</db:guilabel> mode and select the example from <db:guilabel>Examples</db:guilabel>. For more information, visit <db:link xlink:href="https://doc.qt.io/qtcreator/creator-build-example-application.html">Building and Running an Example</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>Example project</db:title>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://code.qt.io/cgit/qt/qtmultimedia.git/tree/examples/multimedia/spectrum?h=6.4">Example project @ code.qt.io</db:link></db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
