<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en_US">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt OpenGL C++ Classes</db:title>
<db:productname>QtOpenGL</db:productname>
<db:titleabbrev>QtOpenGL Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>The Qt OpenGL module offers classes that make it easy to use OpenGL in Qt applications.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>The Qt OpenGL module offers classes that make it easy to use OpenGL in Qt applications.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="namespaces">
<db:title>Namespaces</db:title>
<db:variablelist role="namespaces">
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qgl.xml" xlink:role="namespace">QGL</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QGL namespace specifies miscellaneous identifiers used in the Qt OpenGL module.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
</db:variablelist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="classes">
<db:title>Classes</db:title>
<db:variablelist role="classes">
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qglcontext.xml" xlink:role="class">QGLContext</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QGLContext class encapsulates an OpenGL rendering context.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qglformat.xml" xlink:role="class">QGLFormat</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QGLFormat class specifies the display format of an OpenGL rendering context.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qglwidget.xml" xlink:role="class">QGLWidget</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QGLWidget class is a widget for rendering OpenGL graphics.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
</db:variablelist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="details">
<db:title>Detailed Description</db:title>
<db:warning>
<db:para>Apart from the <db:link xlink:href="qglwidget.xml">QGLWidget</db:link> class, this module should not be used anymore for new code. Please use the corresponding OpenGL classes in <db:link xlink:href="qtgui-index.xml">Qt Gui</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:warning>
<db:para>OpenGL is a standard API for rendering 3D graphics. OpenGL only deals with 3D rendering and provides little or no support for GUI programming issues. The user interface for an OpenGL application must be created with another toolkit, such as Cocoa on the Mac OS X platform, Microsoft Foundation Classes (MFC) under Windows, or Qt on both platforms.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>OpenGL is a trademark of Silicon Graphics, Inc. in the United States and other countries.</db:para>
</db:note>
<db:para>The Qt OpenGL module makes it easy to use OpenGL in Qt applications. It provides an OpenGL widget class that can be used just like any other Qt widget, except that it opens an OpenGL display buffer where you can use the OpenGL API to render the contents.</db:para>
<db:para>To include the definitions of the module's classes, use the following directive:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">#include &lt;QtOpenGL&gt;
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>To link against the module, add this line to your qmake <db:code>.pro</db:code> file:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">QT += opengl
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>The Qt OpenGL module is implemented as a platform-independent Qt/C++ wrapper around the platform-dependent GLX (version 1.3 or later), WGL, or AGL C APIs. Although the basic functionality provided is very similar to Mark Kilgard's GLUT library, applications using the Qt OpenGL module can take advantage of the whole Qt API for non-OpenGL-specific GUI functionality.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
