<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt Positioning on iOS</db:title>
<db:productname>QtPositioning</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.7.2 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Positioning Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Notes on using Qt Positioning on iOS.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:section xml:id="using-qt-positioning-services-from-an-ios-app">
<db:title>Using Qt Positioning Services from an iOS App</db:title>
<db:para>To enable an app to use positioning services on an iOS device, entries must be added to the Info.plist file based on whether the positioning services are needed when the app is in use or when the app is running in the background.</db:para>
<db:para>Once the permission is added, the user needs to grant the permission for the positioning services to be available when the app requests the positioning service. The user can change this by going into Settings &gt; Privacy &gt; Location Services, scrolling down to find the app, and selecting an option. The location services must be on for the positioning services to work.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="using-foreground-location-services-permission">
<db:title>Using Foreground Location Services Permission</db:title>
<db:para>If an app makes use of the positioning services when it is running, the Info.plist file needs to have an entry with the key <db:code>NSLocationWhenInUseUsageDescription</db:code> and a value with a text string giving the user the reason the app makes use of it.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;NSLocationWhenInUseUsageDescription&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;The reason why the app needs location services&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;
</db:programlisting>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="use-background-location-services-permission">
<db:title>Use Background Location Services Permission</db:title>
<db:para>If the app makes use of location services even when it is running in the background, there needs to be an entry with the key <db:code>NSLocationAlwaysAndWhenInUseUsageDescription</db:code> and the reason as string value as well as <db:code>NSLocationWhenInUseUsageDescription</db:code>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;NSLocationWhenInUseUsageDescription&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;The reason why the app needs location services&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;NSLocationAlwaysAndWhenInUseUsageDescription&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;The reason why the app needs location services&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;
</db:programlisting>
<db:note>
<db:para>The Info.plist file is automatically generated, and changes made can be overwritten by qmake or CMake unless measures are taken. See <db:link xlink:href="ios-platform-notes.xml">Platform Notes - iOS</db:link> for more information.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:section>
</db:section>
</db:article>
