<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>JavaScriptCore Macro Assembler</db:title>
<db:productname>QtQml</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.8.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Qml Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>BSD 2-clause &quot;Simplified&quot; License.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:anchor xml:id="masm"/>
<db:para>Used in Qt QML.</db:para>
<db:para>The sources can be found in qtdeclarative/src/3rdparty/masm.</db:para>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://trac.webkit.org/wiki/JavaScriptCore">Project Homepage</db:link></db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">Copyright (C) 2003-2018 Apple Inc. All rights reserved.
Copyright (C) 2007 Justin Haygood (jhaygood@reaktix.com)
Copyright (C) 2007-2009 Torch Mobile, Inc. All rights reserved. (http://www.torchmobile.com/)
Copyright (C) 2009, 2010 University of Szeged
Copyright (C) 2009-2011 STMicroelectronics. All rights reserved.
Copyright (C) 2010 MIPS Technologies, Inc. All rights reserved.
Copyright (C) 2010 Peter Varga (pvarga@inf.u-szeged.hu), University of Szeged
Copyright (C) 2010 MIPS Technologies, Inc. All rights reserved.
Copyright (C) 2010, 2011 Research In Motion Limited. All rights reserved.
Copyright (C) 2011 Google Inc. All rights reserved.
Copyright (C) 2013 Samsung Electronics. All rights reserved.
Copyright (C) 2015 Cisco Systems, Inc. All rights reserved.
Copyright (c) 2002-2009 Vivek Thampi
</db:programlisting>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://spdx.org/licenses/BSD-2-Clause.html">BSD 2-clause &quot;Simplified&quot; License</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">Copyright (C) 2012 Apple Inc. All rights reserved.

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
are met:
1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
   notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
   notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
   documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY APPLE INC. ``AS IS'' AND ANY
EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL APPLE INC. OR
CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL,
EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR
PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY
OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
(INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
</db:programlisting>
</db:article>
