<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt Quick Examples - Views</db:title>
<db:productname>QtQuick</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.12.12 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Quick Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>This is a collection of QML model-view examples.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:programlisting language="qml">/****************************************************************************
**
** Copyright (C) 2017 The Qt Company Ltd.
** Contact: https://www.qt.io/licensing/
**
** This file is part of the examples of the Qt Toolkit.
**
** $QT_BEGIN_LICENSE:BSD$
** Commercial License Usage
** Licensees holding valid commercial Qt licenses may use this file in
** accordance with the commercial license agreement provided with the
** Software or, alternatively, in accordance with the terms contained in
** a written agreement between you and The Qt Company. For licensing terms
** and conditions see https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions. For further
** information use the contact form at https://www.qt.io/contact-us.
**
** BSD License Usage
** Alternatively, you may use this file under the terms of the BSD license
** as follows:
**
** &quot;Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
** modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
** met:
**   * Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
**     notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
**   * Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
**     notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
**     the documentation and/or other materials provided with the
**     distribution.
**   * Neither the name of The Qt Company Ltd nor the names of its
**     contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived
**     from this software without specific prior written permission.
**
**
** THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
** &quot;AS IS&quot; AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
** LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR
** A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
** OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
** SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT
** LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
** DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY
** THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
** (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
** OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.&quot;
**
** $QT_END_LICENSE$
**
****************************************************************************/

import QtQuick 2.0

ListModel {
    ListElement {
        title: &quot;Pancakes&quot;
        picture: &quot;content/pics/pancakes.jpg&quot;
        ingredients: &quot;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
                       &amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 cup (150g) self-raising flour
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 tbs caster sugar
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 3/4 cup (185ml) milk
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 egg
                       &amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
                      &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&quot;
        method: &quot;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
                  &amp;lt;ol&amp;gt;
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Sift flour and sugar together into a bowl. Add a pinch of salt.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Beat milk and egg together, then add to dry ingredients. Beat until smooth.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Pour mixture into a pan on medium heat and cook until bubbles appear on the surface.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Turn over and cook other side until golden.
                  &amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt;
                 &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&quot;
    }
    ListElement {
        title: &quot;Fruit Salad&quot;
        picture: &quot;content/pics/fruit-salad.jpg&quot;
        ingredients: &quot;* Seasonal Fruit&quot;
        method: &quot;* Chop fruit and place in a bowl.&quot;
    }
    ListElement {
        title: &quot;Vegetable Soup&quot;
        picture: &quot;content/pics/vegetable-soup.jpg&quot;
        ingredients: &quot;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
                       &amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 onion
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 turnip
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 potato
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 carrot
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 head of celery
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 1/2 litres of water
                       &amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
                      &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&quot;
        method: &quot;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
                  &amp;lt;ol&amp;gt;
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Chop vegetables.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Boil in water until vegetables soften.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Season with salt and pepper to taste.
                  &amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt;
                 &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&quot;
    }
    ListElement {
        title: &quot;Hamburger&quot;
        picture: &quot;content/pics/hamburger.jpg&quot;
        ingredients: &quot;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
                       &amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 500g minced beef
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Seasoning
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; lettuce, tomato, onion, cheese
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 hamburger bun for each burger
                       &amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
                      &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&quot;
        method: &quot;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
                  &amp;lt;ol&amp;gt;
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Mix the beef, together with seasoning, in a food processor.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Shape the beef into burgers.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Grill the burgers for about 5 mins on each side (until cooked through)
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Serve each burger on a bun with ketchup, cheese, lettuce, tomato and onion.
                  &amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt;
                 &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&quot;
    }
    ListElement {
        title: &quot;Lemonade&quot;
        picture: &quot;content/pics/lemonade.jpg&quot;
        ingredients: &quot;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
                       &amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 cup Lemon Juice
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 1 cup Sugar
                        &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; 6 Cups of Water (2 cups warm water, 4 cups cold water)
                       &amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
                      &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&quot;
        method: &quot;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
                  &amp;lt;ol&amp;gt;
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Pour 2 cups of warm water into a pitcher and stir in sugar until it dissolves.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Pour in lemon juice, stir again, and add 4 cups of cold water.
                   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt; Chill or serve over ice cubes.
                  &amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt;
                 &amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&quot;
    }
}

</db:programlisting>
</db:article>
