<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt Quick Software Adaptation</db:title>
<db:productname>QtQuick</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.0.4 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Quick Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt Quick Reference Documentation.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>The Software adaptation is an alternative renderer for <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-index.xml">Qt Quick</db:link> 2 that uses the Raster paint engine to render the contents of the scene graph, instead of OpenGL. Consequently, some features and optimizations are not available. Most Qt Quick 2 applications can run without any modification, but any attempts to use unsupported features are ignored. By using the Software adaptation, it is possible to run Qt Quick 2 applications on hardware and platforms that do not have OpenGL support.</db:para>
<db:para>The Software adaptation was previously known as the Qt Quick 2D Renderer. However, unlike the 2D Renderer, this new, integrated version supports partial updates. This means that a full update of the window or screen contents is now avoided; only the changed areas are flushed. Partial updates can significantly improve performance for many applications.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="shader-effects">
<db:title>Shader Effects</db:title>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-shadereffect.xml">ShaderEffect</db:link> components in <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-module.xml">QtQuick</db:link> 2 cannot be rendered by the Software adaptation.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="particle-effects">
<db:title>Particle Effects</db:title>
<db:para>It is not possible to render particle effects with the Software adaptation. Whenever possible, remove particles completely from the scene. Otherwise, they will still require some processing, even though they are not visible.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="rendering-text">
<db:title>Rendering Text</db:title>
<db:para>The text rendering with the Software adaptation is based on software rasterization and does not respond as well to transformations such as scaling, compared to when using OpenGL. The quality is similar to choosing <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-text.xml#renderType-prop">Text.NativeRendering</db:link> with <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-text.xml">Text</db:link> items.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="qt-multimedia-videooutput">
<db:title>Qt Multimedia VideoOutput</db:title>
<db:para>The Qt Multimedia module's VideoOutput item is not supported with the Software adaptation. This is because VideoOutput uses the QVideoRendererControl item which requires custom <db:link xlink:href="qsggeometrynode.xml">QSGGeometryNode</db:link> behavior, which is only present in the default OpenGL adaptation.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
