<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt Quick 3D Effects QML Types</db:title>
<db:productname>QtQuick3D</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt Quick 3D | Commercial or GPLv3</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Quick 3D Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Provides QML types for the effects included in the Qt Quick 3D effect library.</db:para>
<db:para>This module is deprecated since 6.5. We strongly advise against using it in new code.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>This module is deprecated since 6.5. We strongly advise against using it in new code.</db:para>
<db:anchor xml:id="details"/>
<db:para>Use <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick3d-helpers-extendedsceneenvironment.xml">ExtendedSceneEnvironment</db:link>, <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-effects-multieffect.xml">MultiEffect</db:link>, or user-defined effects via the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick3d-effect.xml">Effect</db:link> type instead.</db:para>
<db:warning>
<db:para>All pre-made standalone effects in <db:link xlink:href="qtquick3d-qmlmodule.xml">QtQuick3D</db:link>.Effects are considered deprecated starting with Qt 6.5. Instead, to get high quality, high performing implementations of post-processing effects performed by the 3D renderer, such as depth of field, glow and bloom, lens flare, vignette, color adjustments and grading, fog, or ambient occlusion, use <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick3d-helpers-extendedsceneenvironment.xml">ExtendedSceneEnvironment</db:link>. It offers better performance, better visual quality, better interoperation when combining effects, for instance proper support for tonemapping, and is a better fit for visual design tools such as Qt Design Studio. For 2D effects that do not need to be performed within the 3D scene, such as bluring the content of a <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick3d-view3d.xml">View3D</db:link> item, use <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-effects-multieffect.xml">MultiEffect</db:link> on the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick3d-view3d.xml">View3D</db:link> (or a parent of it). If none of these are suitable, applications can provide their own post-processing effects via the <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick3d-effect.xml">Effect</db:link> type.</db:para>
</db:warning>
</db:article>
