<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Open Asset Import Library, version 5.2.3</db:title>
<db:productname>QtQuick3D</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt Quick 3D | Commercial or GPLv3</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Quick 3D Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>BSD 3-clause &quot;New&quot; or &quot;Revised&quot; Licensee.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-01-26</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-01-26</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:anchor xml:id="assimp"/>
<db:para>assimp (Open Asset Import Library) is a portable open source library to import various well-known 3D model formats in a uniform manner.</db:para>
<db:para>Used for importing assets for use with Qt Quick 3D</db:para>
<db:para>The sources can be found in qtquick3d/src/3rdparty/assimp.</db:para>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="http://www.assimp.org/">Project Homepage</db:link>, upstream version: 5.2.3</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">Copyright (c) 2006-2022, assimp team
</db:programlisting>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://spdx.org/licenses/BSD-3-Clause.html">BSD 3-clause &quot;New&quot; or &quot;Revised&quot; Licensee</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">Redistribution and use of this software in source and binary forms,
with or without modification, are permitted provided that the following
conditions are met:

* Redistributions of source code must retain the above
  copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
  following disclaimer.

* Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above
  copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
  following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
  materials provided with the distribution.

* Neither the name of the assimp team, nor the names of its
  contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
  derived from this software without specific prior
  written permission of the assimp team.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
&quot;AS IS&quot; AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR
A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT
LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY
THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
(INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
</db:programlisting>
</db:article>
