<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt Quick Software Adaptation</db:title>
<db:productname>QtQuick</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.8.0 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Quick Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt Quick Reference Documentation.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>The Software adaptation is an alternative renderer for <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-index.xml">Qt Quick</db:link> 2 that uses the Raster paint engine to render the contents of the scene graph instead of OpenGL. As a result of not using OpenGL to render the scene graph, some features and optimizations are no longer available. Most Qt Quick 2 applications will run without modification though any attempts to use unsupported features will be ignored. By using the Software adaptation it is possible to run Qt Quick 2 applications on hardware and platforms that do not have OpenGL support.</db:para>
<db:para>The Software adaptation was previously known as the Qt Quick 2D Renderer. However, unlike the 2D Renderer, the new, integrated version supports partial updates. This means that the full update of the window or screen contents is now avoided, and only the changed areas get flushed. This can significantly improve performance for many applications.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="shader-effects">
<db:title>Shader Effects</db:title>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-shadereffect.xml">ShaderEffect</db:link> components in <db:link xlink:href="qtquick-module.xml">QtQuick</db:link> 2 can not be rendered by the Software adptation.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="qt-graphical-effects-module">
<db:title>Qt Graphical Effects Module</db:title>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qtgraphicaleffects-index.xml">Qt Graphical Effects</db:link> uses <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-shadereffect.xml">ShaderEffect</db:link> items to render effects. If you use graphical effects from this module, then you should not hide the source item so that the original item can still be rendered.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="particle-effects">
<db:title>Particle Effects</db:title>
<db:para>It is not possible to render particle effects with the Software adaptation. Whenever possible, remove particles completely from the scene. Otherwise they will still require some processing, even though they are not visible.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="rendering-text">
<db:title>Rendering Text</db:title>
<db:para>The text rendering with the Software adaptation is based on software rasterization and does not respond as well to transformations such as scaling as when using OpenGL. The quality is similar to choosing <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-text.xml#renderType-prop">Text.NativeRendering</db:link> with <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtquick-text.xml">Text</db:link> items.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
