<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt Script C++ Classes</db:title>
<db:productname>QtScript</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.6.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>QtScript Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>The Qt Script module provides classes for making Qt applications scriptable.</db:para>
<db:para>This module was introduced in Qt 4.3.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para>The Qt Script module provides classes for making Qt applications scriptable.</db:para>
<db:para>This module was introduced in Qt 4.3.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="classes">
<db:title>Classes</db:title>
<db:variablelist role="classes">
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptclass.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptClass</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptClass class provides an interface for defining custom behavior of (a class of) Qt Script objects.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptclasspropertyiterator.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptClassPropertyIterator</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptClassPropertyIterator class provides an iterator interface for custom Qt Script objects.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptcontext.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptContext</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptContext class represents a Qt Script function invocation.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptcontextinfo.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptContextInfo</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptContextInfo class provides additional information about a QScriptContext.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptengine.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptEngine</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptEngine class provides an environment for evaluating Qt Script code.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptengineagent.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptEngineAgent</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptEngineAgent class provides an interface to report events pertaining to QScriptEngine execution.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptextensionplugin.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptExtensionPlugin</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptExtensionPlugin class provides an abstract base for custom QScript extension plugins.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptprogram.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptProgram</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptProgram class encapsulates a Qt Script program.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptstring.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptString</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptString class acts as a handle to &quot;interned&quot; strings in a QScriptEngine.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptsyntaxcheckresult.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptSyntaxCheckResult</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptSyntaxCheckResult class provides the result of a script syntax check.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptvalue.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptValue</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptValue class acts as a container for the Qt Script data types.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptvalueiterator.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptValueIterator</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptValueIterator class provides a Java-style iterator for QScriptValue.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qscriptable.xml" xlink:role="class">QScriptable</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>The QScriptable class provides access to the Qt Script environment from Qt C++ member functions.</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
</db:variablelist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="details">
<db:title>Detailed Description</db:title>
<db:para>The Qt Script module only provides core scripting facilities; the Qt Script Tools module provides additional Qt Script-related components that application developers may find useful.</db:para>
<db:para>This module is mainly provided for backwards compatibility reasons with Qt 4.x and not being actively developed any further. For new code please consider using the <db:link xlink:href="qjsengine.xml">QJSEngine</db:link>, etc. classes in the Qt Qml module instead.</db:para>
<db:para>To include the definitions of the module's classes, use the following directive:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">#include &lt;QtScript&gt;
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>To link against the module, add this line to your <db:link xlink:href="qmake-manual.xml">qmake</db:link> <db:code>.pro</db:code> file:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">QT += script
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>For detailed information on how to make your application scriptable with Qt Script, see <db:link xlink:href="qtjavascript.xml">Making Applications Scriptable</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="license-information">
<db:title>License Information</db:title>
<db:para>Qt Commercial Edition licensees that wish to distribute applications that use the Qt Script module need to be aware of their obligations under the GNU Library General Public License (LGPL).</db:para>
<db:para>Developers using the Open Source Edition can choose to redistribute the module under the appropriate version of the GNU LGPL.</db:para>
<db:para>Commercial customers that do not want to depend on LGPL code can consider using the <db:link xlink:href="qjsengine.xml">QJSEngine</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="qjsvalue.xml">QJSValue</db:link> classes in the Qt Qml module. These classes offer a similar but more narrow scripting API that is sufficient for most use cases and is not dependent on LGPL code.</db:para>
<db:para>Qt Script is licensed under the GNU Library General Public License. Individual contributor names and copyright dates can be found inline in the code.</db:para>
<db:para>This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU Library General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.</db:para>
<db:para>This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU Library General Public License for more details.</db:para>
<db:para>You should have received a copy of the GNU Library General Public License along with this library; see the file COPYING.LIB. If not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:section>
</db:article>
