<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>XSVG</db:title>
<db:productname>QtSvg</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.4.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt SVG Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Historical Permission Notice and Disclaimer - sell variant.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-01-26</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-01-26</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:anchor xml:id="xsvg"/>
<db:para>Some code for arc handling is derived from code from the XSVG project.</db:para>
<db:para>Used in the Qt SVG library.</db:para>
<db:para>The sources can be found in qtsvg/src/svg/qsvghandler.cpp.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">Copyright 2002 USC/Information Sciences Institute
</db:programlisting>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="https://spdx.org/licenses/HPND-sell-variant.html">Historical Permission Notice and Disclaimer - sell variant</db:link>.</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">Copyright  2002 USC/Information Sciences Institute

Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this software
and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted without
fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in all copies
and that both that copyright notice and this permission notice
appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
Information Sciences Institute not be used in advertising or
publicity pertaining to distribution of the software without
specific, written prior permission.  Information Sciences Institute
makes no representations about the suitability of this software for
any purpose.  It is provided &quot;as is&quot; without express or implied
warranty.

INFORMATION SCIENCES INSTITUTE DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD
TO THIS SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL INFORMATION SCIENCES
INSTITUTE BE LIABLE FOR ANY SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL
DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA
OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER
TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR
PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
</db:programlisting>
</db:article>
