<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt WebEngine Licensing</db:title>
<db:productname>QtWebEngine</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.7.2 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt WebEngine Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Qt WebEngine Reference Documentation.</db:para></db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:anchor xml:id="details"/>
<db:para>The Qt WebEngine module uses Chromium to provide most of its functionality. During the build process, Chromium becomes a part of the <db:link xlink:href="qtwebenginecore-index.xml">Qt WebEngine Core</db:link> library. Therefore, when distributing Qt WebEngine, users need to comply to both the licenses of the Qt WebEngine part as developed under the Qt Project, as well as the licenses that are part of Chromium.</db:para>
<db:para>The Qt specific parts of the Qt WebEngine module are available under commercial licenses from The Qt Company. Alternatively, they are available under GNU Lesser General Public License v3.0, or GNU General Public License v3.0, or GNU General Public License v2.0.</db:para>
<db:para>The Chromium part contains code available under various licenses, with the most restrictive license being the <db:emphasis>GNU Lesser General Public License v2.1</db:emphasis> (LGPL 2.1). For a full list, see <db:link xlink:href="qtwebengine-licensing.xml#third-party-licenses">Third-Party Licenses</db:link> below.</db:para>
<db:section xml:id="complying-with-lgpl-2-1">
<db:title>Complying with LGPL 2.1</db:title>
<db:para>The Qt Company allows commercial customers to distribute the source code of the Qt WebEngine module alongside the Qt WebEngine binaries, and allows recipients to customize and build Qt WebEngine from sources. This includes building and using such a modified Qt WebEngine with an application or system using an otherwise commercially licensed Qt.</db:para>
<db:para>The Qt Company also keeps the Qt specific parts of the Qt WebEngine module available under the GNU Lesser General Public License v3.0, or the GNU General Public License v3.0, or the GNU General Public License v2.0, even if <db:link xlink:href="qml-qtwebengine-webengine.xml">WebEngine</db:link> is released as part of a commercial-only Long-Term Support release (LTS, see also <db:link xlink:href="qt-releases.xml#long-term-support-releases">Long-Term Support releases</db:link>).</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="third-party-licenses">
<db:title>Third-Party Licenses</db:title>
<db:para>Third party licenses included in the sources as part of Chromium are found below.</db:para>
<db:note>
<db:para>Any GPL licenses listed below are only used to access Linux system resources. The Qt WebEngine libraries and plugins does not link to nor distribute GPL binary code, and it does not affect users of Qt WebEngine.</db:para>
</db:note>
</db:section>
<db:section>
<db:title>Contents</db:title>
<db:variablelist role="members">
<db:varlistentry>
<db:term><db:link xlink:href="qtwebengine-3rdparty-chromium-global.xml" xlink:role="page">Chromium License</db:link></db:term>
<db:listitem>
<db:para>BSD</db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:varlistentry>
</db:variablelist>
</db:section>
</db:article>
