<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Qt WebEngine Widgets</db:title>
<db:productname>QtWebEngine</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 6.7.2 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt WebEngine Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>Provides a web browser engine as well as C++ classes to render web content and interact with it.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2024-12-27</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2024-12-27</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:section xml:id="getting-started">
<db:title>Getting Started</db:title>
<db:para>To link against the module, add this line to your qmake project file:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">QT += webenginewidgets
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>For build with CMake use the <db:code>find_package()</db:code> command to locate the needed module components in the Qt6 package and <db:code>target_link_libraries()</db:code> to link against the module:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">find_package(Qt6 REQUIRED COMPONENTS WebEngineWidgets)
target_link_libraries(target PRIVATE Qt6::WebEngineWidgets)
</db:programlisting>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="articles-and-guides">
<db:title>Articles and Guides</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qtwebengine-overview.xml">Qt WebEngine Overview</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qtwebenginewidgets-qtwebkitportingguide.xml">Porting from Qt WebKit to Qt WebEngine</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="examples">
<db:title>Examples</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="webengine-widgetexamples.xml">Qt WebEngine Widgets Examples</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="api-reference">
<db:title>API Reference</db:title>
<db:itemizedlist>
<db:listitem>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="qtwebenginewidgets-module.xml">Qt WebEngine Widgets C++ Classes</db:link></db:para>
</db:listitem>
</db:itemizedlist>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="license-information">
<db:title>License Information</db:title>
<db:para>This is a snapshot of the integration of Chromium into Qt.</db:para>
<db:para>Qt Commercial Edition licensees that wish to distribute applications that use the Qt WebEngine module need to be aware of their obligations under the GNU Library General Public License (LGPLv2).</db:para>
<db:para>Developers using the Open Source Edition can choose to redistribute the module under the GNU LGPLv3 or GPLv2 and up.</db:para>
<db:para>Chromium is licensed under the following license:</db:para>
<db:para>Copyright (c) 2013 The Chromium Authors. All rights reserved.</db:para>
<db:para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:</db:para>
<db:para>* Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer. * Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution. * Neither the name of Google Inc. nor the names of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without specific prior written permission.</db:para>
<db:para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS &quot;AS IS&quot; AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
