<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>x86inc</db:title>
<db:productname>QtWebEngine</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.7.1 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt WebEngine Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>ISC from text in file header. Same text is copied to LICENSE file.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:para><db:emphasis role="bold">&lt;Unknown command&gt;<db:code>contentspage</db:code></db:emphasis>qtwebengine-licensing.html</db:para>
<db:para><db:link xlink:href="http://git.videolan.org/?p=x264.git;a=blob;f=common/x86/x86inc.asm">Project Homepage</db:link></db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp" role="bad">;*****************************************************************************
;* x86inc.asm
;*****************************************************************************
;* Copyright (C) 2005-2011 x264 project
;*
;* Authors: Loren Merritt &amp;lt;lorenm@u.washington.edu&amp;gt;
;*          Anton Mitrofanov &amp;lt;BugMaster@narod.ru&amp;gt;
;*          Jason Garrett-Glaser &amp;lt;darkshikari@gmail.com&amp;gt;
;*
;* Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
;* purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
;* copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.
;*
;* THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &quot;AS IS&quot; AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
;* WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
;* MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
;* ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
;* WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
;* ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
;* OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
;*****************************************************************************

; This is a header file for the x264ASM assembly language, which uses
; NASM/YASM syntax combined with a large number of macros to provide easy
; abstraction between different calling conventions (x86_32, win64, linux64).
; It also has various other useful features to simplify writing the kind of
; DSP functions that are most often used in x264.

; Unlike the rest of x264, this file is available under an ISC license, as it
; has significant usefulness outside of x264 and we want it to be available
; to the largest audience possible.  Of course, if you modify it for your own
; purposes to add a new feature, we strongly encourage contributing a patch
; as this feature might be useful for others as well.  Send patches or ideas
; to x264-devel@videolan.org .
</db:programlisting>
</db:article>
