<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<db:article xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:lang="en">
<db:info>
<db:title>Windows CE - Introduction to using Qt</db:title>
<db:productname>QtDoc</db:productname>
<db:edition>Qt 5.6.3 Reference Documentation</db:edition>
<db:titleabbrev>Qt Reference Documentation</db:titleabbrev>
<db:abstract>
<db:para>An introduction to Qt for Windows CE developers.</db:para>
</db:abstract>
<db:pubdate>2025-06-29</db:pubdate>
<db:date>2025-06-29</db:date>
<db:authorgroup>
<db:author>
<db:orgname class="corporation">The Qt Company Ltd.</db:orgname>
</db:author>
</db:authorgroup>
</db:info>
<db:section xml:id="required-tools">
<db:title>Required Tools</db:title>
<db:para>In order to use Qt for Windows CE you need to have Visual Studio 2005 or 2008 and at least one of the supported Windows CE/Mobile SDKs installed. Note, that the Visual Studio 2008 Standard Edition doesn't come with Windows CE support. You will need the Professional Edition, if you're using Visual Studio 2008.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="installing-qt">
<db:title>Installing Qt</db:title>
<db:para>Follow the instructions found in <db:link xlink:href="install-wince.xml">Installing Qt for Windows CE</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="building-your-own-applications">
<db:title>Building Your Own Applications</db:title>
<db:para>If you are new to Qt development, have a look at <db:link xlink:href="overviews-main.xml">Qt Overviews</db:link> and <db:link xlink:href="qtexamplesandtutorials.xml">Tutorials</db:link>. In general there is little or no difference in developing Qt applications for Windows CE compared to any of the other platforms supported by Qt.</db:para>
<db:para>Once you have a .pro file, you can build from the command line. Simply write:</db:para>
<db:programlisting language="cpp">qmake
nmake
</db:programlisting>
<db:para>For more information on how to use qmake have a look at the <db:link xlink:href="winrt-support.xml#getting-started">qmake Tutorial</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
<db:section xml:id="running-the-application">
<db:title>Running the Application</db:title>
<db:para>In order to run the application, it needs to be deployed on the Windows CE/Mobile device you want to test it for. This can either be done manually or automated using Visual Studio.</db:para>
<db:para>To do it manually, simply copy the executable, the Qt .dll files needed for the application to run, and the C-runtime library into a folder on the device, and then click on the executable to start the program. You can either use the <db:emphasis>Explorer</db:emphasis> found in ActiveSync or the <db:emphasis>Remote File Viewer</db:emphasis> found in Visual Studio to do this.</db:para>
<db:para>Further information on deploying Qt applications for Windows can be found in the <db:link xlink:href="windows-deployment.xml">deployment document</db:link>.</db:para>
</db:section>
</db:article>
